<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<glossary>
  <terms>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[A]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Absorb]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[To drink in a substance. Almost any animals living in an aquatic or wetland habitats suffer more from pesticide exposure than animals living on dry land, primarily because wetland organisms absorb so much more pesticide from water.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Acaracides]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The pesticides used to control ticks.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Acetylcholinesterase]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Deactivates the messenger enzyme, acetylcholine, allowing animals to control voluntary muscles. When pesticides bind to acetylcholinesterase, muscle contractions can't be controlled.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Active Ingredients]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The chemical(s) in a product responsible for pesticidal activity; what makes the bug die!]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Acute Toxicity]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A near-immediate reaction to a chemical that causes injury or even death from a single dose or exposure within 24 hours of the exposure.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Adjuvants]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Substance other than the active ingredient of a pesticide e.g., surfactant, spreader-sticker, or wetting agent, that enhances the coverage of a sprayed-on pesticide.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Adsorb]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[To accumulate a substance on the surface in a condensed layer. Pesticides can make their way to lakes, rivers, and streams in two basic ways. They can hitch a ride with eroding soil by adsorbing, or attaching, to soil particles. Or, they can dissolve in runof water and move with the water as it flows across the surface.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Adsorption]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The clinging of molecules to the surface of particles. Water doesn't enter wood fibers, it just sticks to wood fibers.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Adulterated]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Containing added poisonous or harmful ingredients.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Aerosol]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A fine suspension of solid or liquid particles.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Agent]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(See Pathogen).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Agitation]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Process of stirring or mixing in a sprayer.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Air Force Institute for Occupational Health (AFIOH)]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Air Force Institute for Occupational Health: AFIOHs mission is to promote global health and protect Air Force (AF) warriors and communities by enhancing readiness and effectiveness by developing and implementing creative solutions to operational health problems using the range of tools available including environmental and health surveillance, risk analysis, and consultation.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Air plenum]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A space used to conduct air inside a structure.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Alate]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A winged, primary reproductive termite. (They fly out trying to mate; most die).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Algaecides]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pesticides that kill algae.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Alkaloid]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Any of various organic compounds normally with basic chemical properties and usually containing at least one nitrogen atom in a heterocyclic ring, occurring chiefly in many vascular plants and some fungi. Many alkaloids, such as nicotine, quinine, cocaine, and morphine, are known for their poisonous or medicinal attributes.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Allelopathic]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A plant that suppresses the growth of another plant species due to the release of toxic substances]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Allelopathy]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The production and release of chemical substances by one species that inhibit the growth of other species of plants.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Amino acid synthesis inhibitors]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Herbicides of this class inhibit plant protein formation. Such inhibition interferes with DNA synthesis and cell growth. Glyphosate, or Roundup, interferes with production of chlorophyll, as well as vital enzymes]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Amplifying Host]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Disease recipient in which the pathogen multiplies and can be passed on. Also known as an incidental host]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Analog (Synthetic analog)]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A chemical compound that is structurally similar to another but differs slightly in composition. Pyrethroids are synthetic analogs of the botanical, pyrethrum. Organic chemists have determined the structure of natural pyrethrum, the material derived from living chrysanthemums, and constructed similar molecules, with similar, and even superior, insecticidal properties]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Anaphylactic Shock]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The most severe type of anaphylaxis; will usually lead to death in minutes if left untreated]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Anaphylaxis]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A severe and rapid multi-system allergic reaction that occurs when a person is exposed to a trigger substance, called an allergen, to which they have become sensitized. Minute amounts of allergens may cause a life-threatening anaphylactic reaction. Anaphylaxis may occur after ingestion,inhalation, skin contact or injection of an allergen.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Angoumois grain moth]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Named after Angoumois, a region in France; a small moth, very destructive to wheat and other grain; the larva eats out the interior of the grain, leaving only the shell.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Annual]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Plant that lives only one season.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Antennal Club]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The very tip of the antenna; distinguishing trait for red and confused flour beetle. Seen under the microscope, the last 3 segments of the antennal club of the red flour beetle are markedly larger; for the confused flour beetle the last 4 segments are markedly larger.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Anterior]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Front part or in the front.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Anticoagulants]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Rodenticides that work by destroying the clotting power of the rodent's blood and damaging capillaries. (Example, the Coumarins of which Warfarin is an example; the Indandiones, of which diphacinone is an example).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Anti-fouling agent]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A wood preservative or paint, like tributyl tin oxide (TBTO), that prevents marine organisms (especially barnacles) from attaching to the hull of a ship. Use of TBTO near marine life is now banned.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Antihelminthics]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Category of chemicals used to kill nematodes (roundworms), trematodes (flatworms), and/or cestodes (tapeworms) in humans and animals.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Antivenin]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[An antitoxin that counteracts the effects of venom from the bite of a snake, spider or venomous animal or insect.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Appropriated- fund activities]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Operations for which Congress appropriates funding.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Arachnids]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Any small animals with 8 legs, such as scorpions and spiders.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Aracides]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pesticides that kill mites and ticks.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Araneaea]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[An order the class Arachnida; about 105 families of spiders are known, plus about 10 that are extinct.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Arthropod]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Invertebrate with an exo-skeleton, jointed legs and segmented body, such as flies, moths, crabs and lobsters. The word arthropod is derived from the Greek words arthro, which means joint or segment, and poda, which means foot or appendage. (Many animals with a spinal cord (vertebrates) have a jointed foot, but arthropods are the only invertebrates (animals without a spinal cord) that have a jointed appendage).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Atomized]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Reduced to fine particles or a fine spray.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Attractant]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(1) A substance, such as food or a pheromone (a chemical secreted externally by an organism to send information to members of the same species), that attracts insects or other animals (2) Whatever lures a pest into a habitat, e.g., food, water, harborage (shelter). Chemical control involves the use of pesticides, baits, insect growth regulators, repellants and attractants. Sanitation, a part of facilities management, involves removing attractants, such as food scraps.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Augmentation contract]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[specialized service that is contracted out and in support of an existing government pest management operation, such as: aerial applications, wood treatment, utility pole treatment, large-scale termiticide applications.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Automatic compensation]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The now defunct practice of reimbursing manufacturers when they got stuck with a big inventory of  suspended  or canceled dangerous pesticides.(FIFRA Lite, 1988, ended this practice.) Farmers and applicators may still apply for compensation, but not manufacturers.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Avermectins]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A complex of compounds derived from the soil fungus <i>Streptomyces avermitilis</i>. These pesticides were first introduced in the 1980s. Avermectins are slow acting stomach poisons that are quite persistent in the environment. These insecticides are primarily used as ant and cockroach baits, miticides, and antihelminthics.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Avicides]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pesticides that kill birds.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[B]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Backflow]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A phenomenon in which water is siphoned into a water hose after water pressure drops throughout the system, thus flowing in reverse, or back.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Baffle]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A flat plate that controls or directs the flow of liquid or energy.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Bait]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Insecticide that works slowly and at relatively low doses, such that the social insect takes the insecticide back to the colony before dying.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Bait Shyness]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Phenomenon whereby a rodent only accepts the rodenticide bait the first time. Thereafter, they shun the bait because it is so clear to them that the bait kills. Many of the older rodenticides presented this problem.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Ballooning]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Larvae attach a strand of webbing to a twig and drop down several feet. The wind snaps the web and the larvae travels through the air on a parachute-like web.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Bare Ground Pest Control]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A pest control action that attempts to kill every living plant on an area of land. This strategy is best suited to industrial sites such as electrical transformer yards.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Barnacles]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Marine crustaceans with feathery food-catching appendages; free-swimming as larvae; as adults form a hard shell and live attached to submerged surfaces, such as rocks and ships' bottoms.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Bean Weevil]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[One of two main pests of dry beans and peas (the other being the cowpea weevil). Adults attack legumes either in storage or in the field and may even completely destroy them. The grubs, or larvae, hatch from eggs laid in holes that have been chewed by the female into stored beans or into pods in the field.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Bethel process]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Also known as the full-cell process; a pressure and vacuum system designed to put the maximum preservative into wood.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Biennial]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Plant that lives 2 seasons.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Bilateral symmetry]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A type of body organization in which the left and right hand sides are essentially similar.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Bioaccumulation]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[See Biomagnification.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Biocide]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Type of  pesticide, such as creosote or pentachlorophenol, that kill most living things.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Bioinsecticides]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Insecticides derived from the living world. Bioinsecticides may be materials from long-dead organisms, like petroleum, or insecticides derived from living plants, like nicotine, or even living organisms, like bacteria and nematodes used as pesticides.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Biological Control]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(1) Reduction of pest populations by using living organisms encouraged by man (2) Reduction of pest populations through the use of living organisms encouraged by humans; this includes reproductive and genetic control, bacterial" and viral agents, and the use of predatory insects or mites.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Biological tools (IPM)]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Using living things encouraged by man to control pests (ladybug beetle are released to control aphids on plant).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Biological Vector]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A vector that carries a microorganism which goes through a cycle and replicates in vector and the host. (As opposed to a mechanical vector, like the house fly, which does not replicate the pathogen, but simply picks up a pathogen on its feet from feces and then deposits on human food.)]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Biologically Active]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Substances that impact living organisms by causing some change. In the case of pesticides, the change is usually intended to be fatal. For example, some chemicals intended to kill rodents act by preventing blood clotting and by increasing capillary permeability, causing internal bleeding.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Biomagnification]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The process by which the concentration of a pollutant in animals is increased as it moves upward through the food chain (e.g., egret populations decline after DDT use to kill mosquito larva).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Biopesticide]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Biopesticides differ from traditional, synthetic, chemical pesticides because they are found in nature and affect pests by means other than toxicity. Instead of using a poison, a biopesticide controls the pest in other ways such as suffocation or starvation.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Biotic simplification]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[reduction in biological complexity through the elimination of  a vital component of an ecosystem. Pesticides may eliminate the natural controls and ecological balance provided by native predators and parasites, by eliminating these native predators and parasites.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Bird Flu]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Also known as avian flu, is a type of influenza virulent in birds. Public health officials have an enormous fear that a mutated strain will pass into the human population.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Bleb Formation]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A small swelling on the skin, akin to a blister, caused by a brown treesnake bite.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Book lungs]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Lung-like saccular breathing organs containing numerous thin folds of membrane arranged like the leaves of a book, as in the lungs of many arachnids.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Botanicals]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pesticides, usually insecticides, derived from plant tissue. Examples include nicotine, an effective insecticide, and rotenone, an insecticide also used to kill pest fish species.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Broad Spectrum]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Used effectively to control many different types of pests.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Broad Toxicity]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[When a pesticide kills not one, but a number of different types of pests. Example: Prevail, a pesticide used to kill grass, will also kill fish and invertebrates, thus the label warns against cleaning the hose into nearby waters.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Broadcast]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Method of spraying liquid residual pesticides over a wide areas of land or water.  (Spraying an entire carpet is also a form of broadcast spraying.)]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Brown Treesnake]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Nocturnal, strikes defensively when threatened; feeds on vertebrates, primarily, lizards, birds, and mammals. In Guam, where it was introduced, it has been implicated in the extinction of several vertebrate species, including all native birds.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Buboes]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Swollen lymph nodes, tell-tale symptom of bubonic plague, which appear 2-6 days after being bitten.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Bubonic plague]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A bacterial disease vectored by fleas; this was the cause of the Black Death in the Middle Ages.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Budding]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Means of colony propagation used by Pharaoh's ants and other species in which some reproductive adults and a group of workers splinter off the original colony to start a new one]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Buffering agent]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A material added to a pesticide formulation or to the spray tank to modify the acidity or alkalinity so as to protect the active ingredient from breakdown]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[C]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Calibrated cylinder]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A device used to measure liquid volumes. The cylinder is divided into units such as ounces or milliliters and centiliters (for metric measurements). ]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Calibration]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Any adjustment made to the equipment or spray mixture in order to apply a specific amount of pesticide to a given target site.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Calibration constant]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[5940; number used in the formula for converting gallons per acre (gpa) to gallons per minute; derived by obtaining the product of  the square feet in an acre (43,560 square feet), the minutes in an hour and the inches in a foot, and dividing that product by the feet in a mile (5280).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Canceling]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[In an equation, canceling, means to multiply and divide by the same number or unit.  The result is one, which effectively, eliminates like parts of the equation.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Carbamates]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Along with organophosphates, carbamates are highly toxic and the most dangerous group of pesticides. Carbamates and organophosphates kill by cholinesterase inhibition, attack the nervous system, causing loss of muscular control. (Injuries from carbamates are more easily reversible than those of organophosphates.)]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Carbon dioxide Sequestration]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The principle that carbon dioxide can be turned into plant and animal tissue especially wood. As trees grow carbon gets trapped in cellulose and lignin so it's out of the atmosphere for a long time. It's sequestered.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Carpet Beetle]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[All carpet beetle larvae can feed on wool carpets and other wool products, furs, hides, horns, feathers, hair, and silk; also linen, cotton, and rayon if soiled with juice, food, or animal excreta. They can be pests in cereals, stored grains, nuts, meal, Indian corn, red pepper, etc.; also in insect collections and other museum specimens.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Carrier]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[An inert liquid or solid used to carry a pesticide to the pest.  Examples are solvents in which the pesticide is dissolved, granules on which the pesticide is absorbed, and powders with which the pesticide is mixed.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Caste]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[ A subset of individuals within a colony of social animals (chiefly ants, bees, termites, and wasps) that has a specialized function and is distinguished from other subsets by anatomical differences. Typical insect castes are the queen (the female responsible for reproduction), workers (the usually sterile caretakers of the queen, eggs, and larvae), soldiers (defenders of the colony).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Category I]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Highly toxic pesticide: First Aid or Statement of Practical Treatment is required on label.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Category II]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Moderately toxic pesticide: First Aid or Statement or Practical Treatment is required on label.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Category III]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Slightly toxic pesticide: First Aid or Statement or Practical Treatment not required on front label, but usually placed there.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Category IV]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Virtually non-toxic pesticide: First Aid or Statement of Practical Treatment not required, but usually included.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Caterpillar]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Larval stage of order Lepidoptera (moths and butterflies).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Caution]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Human hazard signal word for pesticides that are slightly toxic to humans. This usually refers to Category III pesticides, although it is legally possible for a Category IV pesticides to bear this signal word]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Cell membrane disrupters]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Herbicides activated by sunlight, producing oxygen compounds that rupture cells and thus destroy plant tissue. Death of the plant can be very rapid. Paraquat and diquat interfere with electron flow, resulting in free radical formation, which destroys plant membranes and cells]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Cellulose]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[ A complex carbohydrate, composed of glucose units, that makes up the cell walls of plants; wood fiber used in paper manufacturing.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Center for Health Promotion and Preventive Medicine (CHPPM):]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[USA CHPPM provides worldwide technical support for preventive medicine, public health and health promotion and wellness services supporting America's Army in garrison and during deployments.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Centrifugal pump]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[ A machine for moving a liquid, such as water, by accelerating it radially outward in an impeller to a surrounding volute casing.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Cephalothorax]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[This is a body region consisting of the head and thorax.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Cerci]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Tail protrusion; appendages attached to the last abdominal segment of some insects; tactile or touch receptors.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Certified Pest Controller]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(Certified Pesticide Applicator) A pesticide applicator who has demonstrated competence (via training and testing) and holds a license to legally apply pesticides, including restricted use pesticides. Applicators may be state and/or DOD certified.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Certified Pest Management Personnel]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Any individual who applies pesticides or supervises the use of pesticides, and who has been authorized to do so by successfully completing a training program approved by the EPA, followed by formal certification by the state. Any individual who applies pesticides or supervises the use of pesticides, and who has been authorized to do so by successfully completing a training program approved by the EPA, followed by formal certification by the Personnel from the Department of Defense or one of the states that certify pesticide applicators.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Chain of Infection]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A model used to explain the progress of infectious disease which links pathogens, reservoirs, hosts and means of transmission.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Chelicera]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(1) One member of the first pair of usually pincer-like appendages of spiders, mites, and other arachnida (2) Paired appendage that arise from the mouth area of arachnidae, in particular scorpions and mites (3) Arthropod jaws; spider chelicerae move in a sciss or-like action; tarantula jaws move in an up and down action.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Chemical tools (IPM)]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Use of pesticides, repellants, growth regulators, and other chemicals to manage pest populations]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Chemists]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Synthesize compounds that have pesticidal activity]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Chemosterilant]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pesticide that prevents sexual reproduction of a pest]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Chitin]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A nitrogenous polysaccharide (sugar and nitrogen) found in arthropod cuticle; gives the cuticle its dark color and strength. (2) A tough semitransparent horny substance; the principal component of the exoskeletons of arthropods and the cell walls of certain fungi.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Chlorinated hydrocarbon]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A category of oldies-but-badies, like DDT, Chlordane and Mirex.  Oddly, a lot of chlorinated hydrocarbons had limited human toxicity (although Dieldren, Endrin, and Endosulfan were VERY toxic).  These pesticides affected the nervous system and caused the injuries you'd expect from nervous system damage. Poisoning victims might experience vomiting, muscular tremors, weakness and numbness, as well as unusual apprehension or excitement.  In worst case scenarios, victims lapsed into convulsions and even died. Tragically, this kind of mishap still occurs in rural areas of Africa with long out-of-date pesticides.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Cholinesterase inhibition]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Effect of organophosphates and carbamates that causes loss of muscle control, leading to total collapse]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Cholinesterase testing]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The Army conducts yearly cholinesterase-testing of pesticide applicators because organophosphates and carbamates are such a deadly class of pesticides, attacking the nervous system.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Choke]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A valve that controls the flow of air into the carburetor; choking the engine is necessary because gasoline droplets don't evaporate well in a cold engine.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Choke lever]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Opens and closes the choke.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Choriomeningitis]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A cerebral meningitis with cellular infiltration of the meninges]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Chronic no-effect level]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A threshold level of exposure to a toxin at which no physiological effect occurs over a 2-year period]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Chronic Toxicity]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A reaction to a chemical that builds up and becomes apparent over a period of time longer than 24 hours, usually after weeks of exposure]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Cigarette Beetle]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[One of the most common household insect pests in Virginia. It can be found throughout the year, but seems to be more common in the fall and winter months. A serious pantry pest, the range of food makes them difficult to control. There have been larval infestations in dried flower arrangements, causing the flowers to drop or all the petals to fall.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Class]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A subdivision of a phylum, containing a group of related orders]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Claws]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Claws are paired appendages arising from the cephelothorax of a crustacean]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Cleistothecia]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A closed spherical membrane structure]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Cold Fogging]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Method of producing ultra-low volume or ultra-low dose aerosols; cold foggers aerosolize pesticides without burning or otherwise subjecting the pesticides to heat. Cold foggers typically force pesticide through incredibly small orifices or spray it onto rapidly spinning disks to atomize the liquid into tiny droplets.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Coleoptera]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[An order of insects with chewing mouthparts, in which the front pair of wings are more or less hardened and form a sheath for the membraneous second pair.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Colubrids]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Any of numerous, widely-distributed, chiefly non-venomous snakes of the family Colubridae, which includes the king snake, garter snakes, and water snakes.  The brown treesnake is one of the minority of colubrids that is venomous.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Commensal]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Organisms that live with and rely on a host for a benefit but do not harm or benefit the host. For example, small crabs that depend on oyster reefs for refuge are commensal organisms.  (In the case of rodents, commensal may not be the most accurate term, since people do suffer harm.)  Commensalism with rodents is a one-sided relationship in which rodents get their food and water and shelter from humans, and humans just get to live with rats and mice.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Commercial applicator]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[An applicator used for commercial use]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Commercial certification]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A certification authorizing applicators to apply or supervise use of restricted use pesticides for various commercial purposes. DoD pesticide applicators have commercial certification.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Complete Metamorphosis]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A process of development in which the immature form looks and acts differently from the adult; the stages of development are egg, larva, pupa, and adult.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Concentrate]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Refers to the formulated product before it is diluted by the end user, and consists of a certain percentage of active ingredient, and various inert ingredients (such as, emulsifiers, adjuvants, etc.)]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Concentration]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The amount of a substance present in a mixture. There are many different ways to express concentration.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Condemnation Level 1]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The most stringent of the three condemnation levels; assigned to stored product pests that pose the highest human health hazard; the presence of just one pest condemns the whole lot.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Condemnation Level 2]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The presence of 3 insects condemns the product; medical threat, but not as great as level 1.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Condemnation Level 3]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The presence of 7 insects condemns the product; product contamination.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Condemnation Levels]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The 3 levels of human hazard assigned by the Army and used by veterinarians to assess the safety of product pests; condemnation level 1 means just one insect is enough to condemn the whole lot; for level 2--the presence of 3 insects condemns one pound of product; for level 3--the presence of 7 insects condemns one pound of product.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Confused Flour Beetle]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A Tribolium flour beetle; very common pest infesting flour mills, warehouses, and grocery stores; they also feed on grain, beans, dried fruits, nuts, chocolate, and other foods in the house; the most abundant and injurious insect pest of flour mills in the United States. The red and confused flour beetles live in the same environment and compete for resources.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Conifers]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Any of various mostly needle-leaved or scale-leaved, chiefly evergreen, cone-bearing gymnospermous trees or shrubs such as pines, spruces, and firs.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Conjunctiva]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The mucous membrane that lines the inner surface of the eyelids.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Conspicuous]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Easily seen or noticed; readily observable. (Directions for Use must be conspicuously placed on the label.)]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Constant flow valve]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Regulates spray pressure at a certain level. If the valve is designed to operate at 21 pounds per square inch, spray pressure will remain at that level until tank pressure drops below 21 psi. At that point the valve closes and the flow shuts off.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Contact Foliage Applied Herbicide]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A chemical that kills primarily by contact with plant tissue, with little or no translocation.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Control handle]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Allows operator to control the sprayer without taking it off his or her shoulders.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Conversion, pounds to kilograms]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[To do the lethal dose calculation, first convert pounds to kilograms using the formula:  weight in pounds X 2.2.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Cornicles]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Abdominal spikes]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Core Phase]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[That part of an applicator certification course addressing subjects common to all pest management, such as laws and regulations, pesticide safety, label reading and so on. A student must successfully complete the core phase to gain any kind of certification.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Corvids]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A family of songbirds which includes crows, ravens, magpies and jays.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Cost-Conscious Pest Control]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Originated by farmers concerned about the bottom-line. Example: It will cost you $1,000 for judicious use of some pesticide in conjunction with other control measures. Left untreated you can expect $1,999 in pest damages. By spending $1,000 you save $999 in damages. This is a good deal for your pocketbook and a good deal for the environment.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Coxal glands]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[In certain arthropods, a pair of excretory organs consisting of an end sac where initial urine is collected, a tubule where secretion and re-absorption may take place, and an excretory pore at the base (coxa) of one of the legs.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Crustacean]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Any of various predominantly aquatic arthropods of the class Crustacea, including lobsters, crabs, shrimps, and barnacles, characteristically having a segmented body, a chitinous exoskeleton, and paired jointed limbs.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Cubed]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Multiplying a number by itself 3 times, or raising a number to the third power e.g. 3³.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Culex]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A mosquito genus.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Cultural tools (IPM)]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Non-chemical alteration of the environment (sanitation, draining surface waters, removing pest habitat).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Curative Pesticide]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A chemical used to kill or inhibit existing pest infestations. This type of pesticide is commonly used to control existing fungal infestations.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Customer Education]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Arguably the most important step in IPM; teaching the customer about good facilities management, to include, structural repairs, maintenance, and sanitation. Proper maintenance and housekeeping will prevent pest problems from occurring in the first place.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Cutaneous]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Affecting or existing on the skin surface; as in cutaneous leishmaniasis.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Cutaneous Leishmaniasis]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A form of leishmaniasis that causes lesions on the skin surface.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Cuticle]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Epidermis, outer skin of insect.  The non-cellular outer wall of the arthropod exoskeleton, composed of chitin.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[D]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[D.]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Dust. As in Turflon D]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Danger]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Human hazard signal word for Category I pesticides that are very toxic to humans by virtue of local eye and skin effects only.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Danger - Poison]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Human hazard signal word for Category I pesticides that are very toxic to humans by oral, dermal, or inhalation exposure.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[DD Form 1532]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The 1532-1 is a record, but NOT a report. Installations REPORT pest management activities for the entire installation on the DD Form 1532, its electronic equivalent. Using the daily records of pest management activities, the 1532 tells the command all about pest management on a given installation. On the 1532, all the pesticide usage traceable in terms of pounds of active ingredient, as well as other control activities like surveillance and trapping are reported. Every organization that applies pesticides MUST report that usage to the pest management coordinator. In the past, everyone submitted the 1532 once a month, but now, different commands may require reporting once a quarter, or even once a year.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[DD Form 1532-1]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The DD Form 1532-1 is the ONLY military form that records pest management BY FACILITY! Remember, a facility can be a building, parade ground, ball field, or a road side ditch.  It's where the pesticide is applied and allows someone to identify the place of repeated applications of pesticide. A lot of military installations around the country are being closed, and the DD Form 1532-1 is used to help with pre-closure environmental condition surveys. It's good to know where DDT or chlordane or other persistent pesticides have gone.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Dead-End Host]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Disease recipient that dies or recovers without passing on the disease.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Dengue fever]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A viral disease vectored by mosquitoes; also known as break bone fever.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Deregistered pesticides]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pesticides for which the EPA hs removed registration due to safety/environmental issues or at the manufacturer's request.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Dermal (and oral) toxins]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Toxins absorbed through the skin (or ingested through the mouth). Measured using LD50 values.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Dermal absorption]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Occurs when a toxin is allowed to contact and penetrate skin. Any pesticide containing oil or solvents can be absorbed through unprotected human skin. A pesticide applicator applies pesticide, then uses the rest room without first washing his hands.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Dermestid Beetles]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Beetles belonging to the family Dermestidae, such as:  larder, carpenter, furniture carpenter and khapra beetles.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Desiccating pesticide]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pesticide that kills the target pest by mechanical means. Specifically, it abrades (rubs off) the waxy coating on the cuticle (outer skin) of insect causing it to dehydrate and die, e.g., dust like silica aerogel or diatomaceous earth. Desiccants work slowly. Thus they wouldn't be appropriate on a pest that stings, such as a yellow jacket wasp.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Desiccation]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(1) Dryness resulting from the removal of water (2) To make or become completely dry]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Deuterocerebrum]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The middle section of the insect brain, formed by the ganglia (nerve center) of the second primary segment. The arthropod "brain" is actually a collection of ganglia compressed into a single organ made up of the:  protocerebrum, deuterocerebrum, and tritocerebrum.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Diameter]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The length of a straight line passing through the center of a circle and connecting two points on the circumference.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Diapause]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(1) Extended rest period of quiescence between periods of growth or reproductive activity (e.g., hibernation in winter, estivation in summer) (2) Period of rest when insects are inactive due to temperature extremes; hibernation in winter, estivation in summer.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Diaphragm pump]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A positive displacement pump that uses a combination of the reciprocating action of a rubber or Teflon diaphragm and suitable non-return check valves to pump a fluid.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Dictyoptera]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Includes three groups of insects, the Isoptera (termites), Blattodea (or Blattaria; cockroaches) and the Mantodea (mantids, or praying mantises). The use of the term Dictyoptera has changed over the years, and while largely out of use for much of the last century, it is becoming more widely used. It is presently usually considered a superorder, with Isoptera, Blattodea and Mantodea being its three orders. In some classifications, however, Dictyoptera is shifted to order status. Regardless, in all classifications, the three constituent groups are the same, just treated at different rank. Termites and roaches are very closely related, and together are the sister group to the mantids.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Diffusion]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Process by which liquids spread through a matrix. Water-borne wood preservatives, like the borates, diffuse through a piece of wood under moist conditions.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Diluent]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(1) A substance used to reduce the percentage of active ingredient of a pesticide. This might be, for example, the water added by a pesticide applicator, or the food bait added by a manufacturer to attract rodents and mask rodenticide. (2) Food bait used to attract the rodent and mask the rodenticide.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Dilution effect]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The larger the space, the larger the dilution effect. Thus, it is always safer to apply pesticides outdoors where dilution is greatest.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Dioxin]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Toxic contaminant deregistered (banned) in 1984.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Direct relationship]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Relationship between two variables a and b in which an increase in a results in the same increase in variable b. There is a direct relationship between nozzle size and flow rate. As the nozzle size increases, the flow rate increases.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Discharge rate]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Synonym for flow rate of pesticide.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Disease Triad]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The 3 elements (vector, pathogen and host) that make vector borne disease transmission possible.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Disease Vectors]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pests which carry disease, e.g., the Anopheles mosquito vectors malaria; body lice vector typhus.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Displacement pump]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Any pump with a pulsing action, produced by compressed air, steam or a plunger.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Dispersing agent]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[An adjuvant that facilitates mixing and suspension of a pesticide formulation in water.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Distal]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Near or towards the free end of an appendage. The part of a segment or appendage that is furthest away from the center of the body.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Disturbed Soil]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Any soil that has been dug up or ploughed. (Argentine ants colonize disturbed soil.)]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Dorsal]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pertaining to the back.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Drift]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(1) Movement of an herbicide away from the target plant and into the atmosphere; caused by rain or wind. (2) The physical movement of pesticide droplets or particles through the air at the time of pesticide application or soon thereafter from the target site to any non or off-target site. Drift can expose people, wildlife, and the environment to pesticide residues that can cause health and environmental effects and property damage. Example: honeybees that are killed far from the actual pesticide application site.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[DRMO]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Defense Reutilization and Marketing Office handles recycling and sale/disposal of obsolete military supplies and equipment. It is responsible for disposing of unwanted but still packaged and labeled pesticides.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Drugstore Beetle]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Attacks such a wide variety of foods and material; Eats anything but cast iron. It gets its name from its habit of feeding on prescription drugs. It also feeds on flours, dry mixes, breads, cookies, chocolates and other sweets, and spices. Non-food material includes wool, hair, leather, horn, and museum specimens. It is found in pigeon nests and is known to bore into books, wooden objects, and in some cases, tin or aluminum foil and lead sheets. Larval feeding accounts for the greatest amount of damage. Museum and herbarium specimens are vulnerable to attack.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Dry boom]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[a type of boom that does not carry liquid.  The boom serves as support for nozzles which are supplied by spray tubing.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Dry flowable]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A dry, granular pesticide formulation that forms a suspension when added to water.  Same as Water Dispersible Granule.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Dust]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A finely ground, dry pesticide formulation containing a small amount of active ingredient and a large amount of inert carrier or diluent such as clay or talc.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[E]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[E or EC]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Emulsifiable concentrate. As in Prograss EC.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Ecdysis]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Molting; the process of shedding the exoskeleton.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Economic Threshold]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Point at which spending money on pest control becomes cheaper than the continued costs of pest damage. During a public health crisis, however, (mosquitoes and West Nile virus, ticks and Lyme disease, or fleas and Bubonic plague) cost is not factored into the equation]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Ecosystem]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Stable and self-sustaining system formed by the interaction of a community of organisms with their environment; a living community.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Ectoparasites]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(1) Fleas, lice, ticks, etc.; organisms that grow, feed, and are sheltered on the outside of another animal while contributing nothing to the survival of its host. (2) Pests such as fleas and lice that feed on living animals from outside, usually by taking blood meals. (3) A parasite, such as the flea, that lives on the outer surface of its host.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Elapidae]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A family of poisonous reptiles, including cobras, kraits, mambas, and coral snakes; all have a pteroglyph fang arrangement (fixed front fangs).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Elephantiasis]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Later complication of Filariasis; swollen lymph nodes and relapses lead to vastly enlarged and deformed extremities.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Emergence holes]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The holes gnawed out by adult wood-feeding beetles as they leave larval tunnels and emerge into the outer world.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Emergent]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Arising from a liquid or other medium. An aquatic plant having its stem leaves, etc., extending above the surface of the water.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Emergent (Secondary) Pest]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pest species that becomes a problem for the ecosystem only after a stronger competitor for the same food source has been removed Pests A and B normally compete for the same food within a given ecosystem. When Pest A is eliminated as a result of a pesticide application, pest B emerges as the new problem and has a field day, aggressively monopolizing the food source. Pest B is now the emergent or secondary pest. Example: Plant mites attack crops after aphid control.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Emulsifiable concentrate]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A pesticide formulation produced by mixing an active ingredient and an emulsifying agent in a suitable petroleum solvent.  When added to water, a milky emulsion is formed.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Emulsifier]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A substance that stabilizes a suspension of droplets of one liquid in another liquid which otherwise would not mix.  Commonly used to facilitate the mixing of an oil in water.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Emulsion]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A mixture in which one liquid is suspended as small droplets in another liquid.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Encapsulated pesticide]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A pesticide formulation with the active ingredient enclosed in capsules of polyvinyl or other synthetic materials.  Used primarily for slow release.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Encephalitis]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A viral disease vectored by mosquitoes and ticks, causing inflammation of the brain and spinal column.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Endemic]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Native to a particular nation, area, or region.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Endoparasite]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A parasite, such as a tapeworm, that lives within another organism]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Endophily]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The urge to enter human dwellings shown by domestic or filth flies, as well as other animals.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[End tag]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Label found at the end of a piece of treated wood. It indicates type and amount of preservative used.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Enteric]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pertaining to the intestines.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Enteric Bacteria]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Bacterial pathogens that transmit intestinal diseases, such as: shigella, typhoid, cholera, salmonellosis, poliomyelitis, tuberculosis, and leprosy.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Entomologists]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Provide biological and taxonomic information about insects and related arthropods.  Evaluate efficacy of pesticides such as insecticides and miticides.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Environmental Hazard]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The product is potentially harmful to wildlife, fish, endangered animals and plants, or may adversely impact wetlands or water resources.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Environmental Performance Assessment Survey (EPAS)]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The EPAS program assists all Army commanders in attaining, sustaining, and monitoring compliance with Federal, State, and local environmental laws and regulations, as well as DoD and Army compliance and performance requirements. EPAS external and internal multi-media assessments: - Identify non-compliance with environmental regulations and non-conformance with the ISO 14001 environmental performance standard used by Army EMS; - Provide suggestions for both immediate and long-term corrective actions; and - Indicate resources needed for implementation.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Environmental safety in IPM]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[an ecosystem-based strategy that attempts to minimize risks to human health, beneficial organisms, and the environment by targeting only target pests, using the least-invasive methods that can do the job, and conforming to restrictions on endangered species.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Enzyme]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A protein molecule that catalyzes (increases the velocity of) chemical reactions of other substances without itself being destroyed or altered upon completion of the reaction.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[EPA]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Environmental Protection Agency. The Federal agency responsible for promulgating and implementing environmental regulations.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[EPA registration number]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Number unique to each chemical; completely identifies the pesticide; the one number that identifies the pesticide like a fingerprint. Using just this number, you can look up all available information on this chemical from the EPA database.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Epidemiology]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The study of epidemics and epidemic diseases.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Epithelium]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(1) A tissue composed of epithelial cells. Such tissue, like the lining of the intestines, tends to surround parts of the body, somewhat like a cell membrane. It is also used to form glands. (2) Thin layer of tissue that covers organs, glands, and other structures within the body. The pathogen, Ricketsia ricketsii, that causes Rocky Mountain Spotted Fever, multiplies in the epithelium of blood vessels.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Epizootic]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[An epidemic of an animal disease, e.g, bluetongue disease in sheep.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Establishment Number]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[This number identifies the final facility where the pesticide was manufactured.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Estivation]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Period of dormancy during the summer, during periods of high temperatures or dry periods.  Seen in mosquitoes that are active in the winter/spring but not in the heat of the summer.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Even spray flat fan nozzle]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[type of nozzle used for row-crop treatment. Nozzles aren't overlapped. Each nozzle produces an even flow all the way across the spray pattern, so that the same ounces per minute is generated from the center and edges of the pattern.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Exit holes]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[See ""Emergence holes.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Exo-Skeletal Insect]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Insect with hardened external support structure, such as crustaceans, turtles, and fish. Arthropods have an outside shell. The exoskeleton of a fly or moth is thin and weak. That of a crab or lobster is thick and strong.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Exoskeleton]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A skeleton or supporting structure that is outside the body]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Extirpated Species]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Species that have become locally extinct since the introduction of European settlements; for example: in Guam, many native species of birds have been extirpated by the browntree snake.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Extrapolation]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Calculation of unknown values from known values. For example, if Jimmy makes $100 a day, we can extrapolate to say that he'll make $1,000 in 10 days.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[F]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[F or FL]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Flowable. As in Guthion 3F]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Facilities Management]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(Better known as Directorate of Public Works on most installations); fixing building issues that would cause a structure to be favorable for pests. Pests are looking for food, water and shelter. Any measure that prevents their access to these three things will help to lower the ir numbers. Thus, DPW would fix a broken screen door that would allow flies access to a kitchen.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Facility]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[For pesticide recording purposes, a facility can be a building, parade ground, ball field, or a road side ditch.  It's where the pesticide is applied and allows someone to identify the place of repeated applications of pesticide.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Facultative Parasites]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Parasites, such as fungi, that can survive either by parasitizing a host, or by some other means, such as living off decaying matter]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Family]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A subdivision of an order, usually ending with the suffix, -idea]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Fan unit]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Provides the air blast that disperses pesticide; actually sprays out liquid pesticide in mist-sized droplets.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Federal stock code]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Series 6840 is assigned to all pesticides, herbicides, fungicides and rodenticides.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Fuel line]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Moves fuel from the tank to the engine.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Filarial Worm]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Several species of small, thread-like parasitic nematode worms known to infect humans, some of them containing the causative agents of river blindness (Onchocerca) and elephantiasis (Brugia, Wuchereria).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Filth Flies]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Flies that live on garbage (house flies, blow flies and flesh flies, and soldier flies*). They pick up pathogenic organisms from sewage, garbage, manure, decaying bodies and other such sources. These flying pests initially pick up dangerous organisms with their mouth and other body parts. The organisms are then passed on to humans and animals through the feces and vomit of the fly.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Finished spray]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Refers to a pesticide mixture with all concentrate, diluent, adjuvants and other materials added, and ready to apply]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Fix]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Make biologically available; as in bacteria in the gut of the termite that make nitrogen biologically available to termites so that they can obtain proteins.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Flagellated]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Having whip-like appendages]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Flash Point]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The lowest temperature at which a liquid will give off sufficient vapor to ignite on application of a flame.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Flashback]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Hazard that may be present near valves on pressurized pesticide cans. In the event of fire, a flashback prevention valve keeps flame from getting back into the container and causing an even bigger problem (an explosion in your hand, for example). It's analogous to backflow prevention valves in plumbing systems.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Flat fan nozzle]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[type of nozzle used on most boom sprayers (except for row crop application). Each spray pattern produces more flow at the center of the nozzle than on the sides, so the patterns can be overlapped to produce even flow across the boom.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Flow Rate]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A measurement used for pesticide spray nozzles. In the United States, nozzles are rated according to the gallons of spray per minute (gpm) they will produce at a certain pressure, measured in pounds per square inch, or psi.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Flowable]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A pesticide formulation in which a very finely ground solid particle is suspended (not dissolved) in a liquid carrier.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Foliar application]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Application of pesticides to plant foliage (the leaves of the plant).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Foraging]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The seeking and obtaining of food.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Formulation]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(1) The mixture of active and other ingredients in a pesticide that affects the active ingredient's solubility. (2) The form in which a pesticide is prepared for practical use (usually this is the product purchased by the pest manager).  Also, the term for the manufacturing process of making a formulation. (3) The manner in which a pesticide's active ingredient is made for practical use.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Frass]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Debris or excrement produced by insects.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Fraud]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Deception, trickery, or breach of contract. Misrepresentation of a product, as to its use, safety, etc.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Fruiting body]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A fungal structure used to produce and disseminate spores: a spore-producing structure.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Full-cell process]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Also known as the Bethel process; a pressure and vacuum system designed to put the maximum preservative into wood.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Fumigant]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(1) Small organic molecules that are gases above 40 degrees Fahrenheit. They are heavier than air and are highly penetrating, but non-persistent. Fumigants are highly toxic. (2) A pesticide that forms gases that are toxic to plants, animals, and microorganisms. (3) PLURAL: Pesticides that actually become a gas after release and infiltrate an enclosed space.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Fungicides]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pesticides that kill fungi.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Fungus]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Any of various organisms such as molds, mildew, mushrooms etc. that lack chlorophyll, stems and leaves and reproduce by spores.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Furniture Carpet Beetle]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[As its name suggests, the furniture carpet beetle is most commonly found feeding at carpet edges, under baseboards, and in upholstered furniture.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[G]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[G.]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[As in Merit O.5G. G stands for granular.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Galleries]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[System of tunnels or nests in wood that are gnawed out by insects such as termites, carpenter ants and beetles.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Galls]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Abnormal growths of plant tissues caused by various parasites, fungi, bacteria, insects, and mites.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Galvanic corrosion]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[An electrochemical action which takes place when dissimilar metals are in contact in the presence of an electrolyte, resulting in corrosion.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Galvanized]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Dipped in zinc. Steel sheets are dipped into molten zinc. Termite shields can be made of galvanized metal as an alternative to the costly copper termite shields. ]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Ganglia]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A gray mass of nerve tissues]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Genus]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A subdivision of a family, the first name in the binomial nomenclature (genus + species) of an organism.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Gestation]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Period of time between fertilization and birth of an animal. Commonly called pregnancy in humans.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[GOCO]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Acronym for Government-Owned, Contractor-Operated. Examples of GOCO facilities include: ammunition storage facilities and Army Family Housing.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[GPM]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Gallons per minute]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Granary Weevils]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Both granary and rice weevils, often known as "Snout weevils", penetrate and feed on the internal portions of whole grains during the larval (immature) stage, making early detection of infestations difficult. Usually found in grain storage or processing plants, infesting wheat, oats, rye, barley, rice, and corn. Although not often found in the home, sometimes they infest table beans, acorns, chestnuts, birdseed, sunflower seeds, and ornamental corn. Rarely found in macaroni and spaghetti.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Green glands]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A pair of excretory organs in each side of the head region of certain crustaceans, emptying at the base of the antennae.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Gribbles]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A very destructive crustacean that colonizes wood in marine environments. Gribbles generally colonize marine pilings and can degrade wood to the point that it's completely destroyed. Gribbles, like shipworms (or teredos) are also referred to as "marine borers" for their wood destroying habits.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Grip]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Link between the operator's hand and the starter rope.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Grooming]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Social behavior whereby termites clean each other, typically removing excess dirt and fungal spores; this is important in the control of pathogens. Where an individual being groomed is deemed to be damaged or unfit, grooming may lead to cannibalism. ]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Ground Water]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Water that is deep under the surface of the earth, as in wells and springs.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Growth Regulators]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pesticides that stimulate or retard the growth of pests by disrupting their normal life cycle.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Guano]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A substance composed chiefly of the dung of sea birds or bats; accumulated along certain coastal areas and caves and used as fertilizer.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[H]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Habitat]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The natural abode or locality of an animal, plant, etc.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Habitat loss]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The destruction of habitats required by wildlife for survival resulting from human population growth and the consumption of open space and resources.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Habitat Manipulation]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Removing or altering a pest habitat (place where pests live and feed) by making it inhospitable; habitat manipulation is an IPM control measure that falls under the category of facilities management.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Half-life]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The time required for the potency of a chemical to fall to half of its potency or to be eliminated from the body. For example, if the potency is 32 with a half-life of 15 years, the potency will be 16 in 15 years and then will drop by half each of the following 15 years to 16, then 8, then 6, etc.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Harborage]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(1) A place of refuge. For pests, the place where they find shelter and food. (2) A place of refuge, where animals, such as rodents find shelter. (3) Place or shelter where pests live. (Removing the harborage may eliminate the pest; facilities management). Structural repairs, such as caulking and sealing will remove the harborage of cockroaches, ants, and silverfish.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Heartwood]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The wood from the central trunk of a mature tree -- containing natural preservative chemicals; modern forestry techniques produces lumber that's all sapwood-very edible for termites.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Heartworms]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Micro filarial worms vectored by mosquitoes: these worms cause heartworm disease in dogs.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Hemi-Hydrobionts]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A group of animals that lives only partially in water, such as horsefly larva, which live in muddy soil.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Hemicellulose]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A carbohydrate which in addition to cellulose and lignin is one of  the most important components of timber.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Hemolymph]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The blood of lower invertebrates. (You do need to know that arachnids, terrestrial or land living arthropods breathe  either through spiracles or book lungs. The spiracles are on the body surface, and take air to individual cells. The book lungs are a stack of thin exoskeleton. An arachnid's hemolymph, or circulatory fluid, travels through the book lungs, becomes oxygenated, and then travels throughout its body.)]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Hemotoxic]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Causing breakdown of the circulatory system. (The venom of the viper is hemotoxic as well as neurotoxic and digests protein, causing tissue damage.)]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Herbicides]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pesticide that kill plants]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Hermaphrodite]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[An arthropod, such as an earthworm (phyla Annelida) or plant, having both male and female reproductive organs.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Hibernation]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A period of lethargy or suspended animation in animals occurring during seasonal low temperatures.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Histoplasmosis]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Respiratory infection caused by fungi that grow in the acid dust under bird or bat droppings.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Honeydew]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Sticky, sugary secretion deposited on plants by insects such as aphid and whitefly and collected by ants.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Horizontal barrier]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Termiticide applied to graded soil or gravel fill under foundation.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Hormone]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A product of living cells that circulates in animal or plant fluids and that produces a specific effect on cell activity remote from its point of origin.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Horticultural oils]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Light petroleum oil mixed with emulsifier. These oils are mixed with water and sprayed over scales and other arthropod species to reduce oxygen intake and kill.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Host]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[An organism capable of contracting a disease.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Host Specific]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(1) An organism that depends upon one particular species of plants, animal, or insect for its food or habitat. For example, the pubic louse lives only on human beings, and only in the pubic hair of its human host. Now THAT'S specific! (2) The characteristic of pests feeding only on one host, even if they starve to death; a form of bio-control is to introduce a new, host-specific species, such as parasitic wasps into a habitat to lay eggs only on a problem pest.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Human Hazard Signal Words]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Required on the front panel of the label, these words describe a hierarchy of pesticide toxicity to humans. From least to most toxic, they are: 1. Caution (Slightly toxic), 2. Warning (Moderately toxic), 3. Danger (Highly toxic eye effects), 4. Danger-Poison (Highly toxic - dermal, oral, inhalation). The human hazard level is indicated in Area 7 of the label: human hazard signal words]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Hydramethylnon]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The active ingredient in AMDRO; a slow-acting stomach poison that prevents the insect from making ATP (Energy).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Hydrobionts]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A group of animals that lives mostly in water, such as deerfly larva.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Hydrocele]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Later complication of Filariasis; accumulation of serous fluid in the testes.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Hydrophidae]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Any of numerous venomous aquatic viviparous snakes having a fin-like tail; of warm coastal seas; feed on fish which they immobilize with quick-acting venom]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Hydrostatic pressure]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The pressure exerted by a fluid at equilibrium at a given point within the fluid, due to the force of gravity]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Hymenoptera]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[An order of insects with membranous wings and chewing mouthparts, including: bees; wasps; ants; ichneumons; sawflies; gall wasps and so on.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Hymenopterans]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Insects belonging to the order hymenoptera and having membranous wings; a wasp is a hymenoptera (singular),  wasps, bees, and ants are all hymenoptera (plural); many hymenopterans are venomous insects (though, not all ants are veno" mous)]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Hypercalcemia]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Leaching of calcium from the bones into the bloodstream, producing elevated blood calcium levels. The anti-coagulant rodenticide, Cholecalciferol (Vitamin D3) causes death by hypercalcemia, leading to cardiac arrest, by leaching calcium from the rodent's bones into it's bloodstream.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Hyperparsitism]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A condition in which a secondary parasite develops within a previously existing parasite.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Hypha]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(plural, hyphae) One of the filament-like threads that makes up the body of a fungus. Any of the threadlike filaments forming the mycelium of a fungus.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Hypopus]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Diapause or dormant phase of mite nymphs; during this phase mites are resistant to almost any control technique.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[I]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Identifying Information]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[For each pesticide, there are nearly a half-dozen pieces of identifying information that must be entered:  trade name, formulation, NSN, EPA no., unit of issue, unit of measurement, total amount received, amount on hand, active ingredient, conversion factor. (All of these can be found on the label except for the NSN, total received, amount on hand, and the conversion factor.)]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[IGR]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Insect growth regulator. As in Gentrol IGR Concentrate. IGRs prevent maturation of insects, and in some cases disrupt chitin (a component of the exoskeleton) synthesis.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Illegal Application]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Any application contrary to the label directions.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Imadacloprid]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The active ingredient (a.i) in MERIT; mimics the action of nicotine in the insect; nerve poison.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Immediately dangerous to life and health]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The maximum level of a contaminant (usually measured in parts per million) to which a healthy individual can be exposed for 30 minutes and escape without suffering irreversible health effects or impairing" symptoms. For example, you might be able to work for 30 minutes in an atmosphere containing 2 parts per million of chemical X, whereas at 3 ppm you'd immediately collapse.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Impeller]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[any person or thing that impels, as the rotor-like part in a water pump.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Inactive Ingredients]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Other ingredients besides the active ingredient, that affect solubility (ability to stick) and other functions. Also known as adjuvants.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Incidental Host]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(See Amplifying Host).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Incising]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A process by which uniform cuts are made in the wood to improve the penetration of wood preservatives.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Indian Meal Moth]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A minor to significant pantry pest of stored dried food materials. Infestations can be persistent, requiring cleanliness and exclusion practices such as hermetically sealed containers for food.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Inert Ingredients]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Substances in a pesticide that are not the actual active (toxic) ingredient. They may include solvents, diluents, synergists, and other additives. The percentage (but not usually the chemical name or composition) must be listed" as part of the statement of ingredients. Also see inactive ingredients.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Inguinal]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pertaining to the area of the groin.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Inhalation Absorption]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The most dangerous form of exposure (as compared to dermal and oral absorption) because the lungs absorb almost 100 percent of the toxin within 30 minutes.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Inhaled toxins]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Toxic vapors, fumigants, or finely-ground dusts, that are taken inhaled, especially when applied indoors.  This happens to pesticide applicators who fail to use a respirator when needed. They are measured using LC50 values.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Initial assessment]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[series of five questions that you should ask in order to size up the situation and determine if there is, in fact, a pest management problem that warrants developing an IPM strategy.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Inorganic Compounds]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The oldest group of rodenticides; these contain no carbon. They were too lethal for humans, and animals, and they were persistent (they never broke down),  remaining in the atmosphere for years. One exception is white phosphorus, but it too is a highly toxic, restricted use, category I rodenticide. It must be mixed underwater.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Inorganic Insecticides]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Contain no carbon at all.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Inorganic Pesticides]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(Made from metals, they don't contain carbon.) Lead arsenate, a form of arsenic is still used; but this category has been largely replaced by the synthetic insecticides. Exposure causes vomiting, bloody diarrhea, headache, dizziness, cramps, and destruction of the intestinal lining, if swallowed.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Insect Growth Regulators]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pesticides that stimulate or retard the growth of pests by disrupting their normal life cycle.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Insect Order Dictyoptera]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[See Dictyoptera.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Insecticidal Soap]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Soap that coats the spiracles (air/water passages), blocking the flow of air and causing quick suffocation.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Insecticides]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pesticides that kill insects.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Installation Medical Authority (IMA)]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[IMA is at the center of the Army's initiative to mold installation support functions into a corporate structure, enabling equitable, efficient and effective management of Army installations worldwide. The IMA supports readiness, promotes well-being of soldiers, civilians and family members, and preserves infrastructure and the environment.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Instar]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Molting stage of young immature insect: 1st instar, 2nd instar, 3rd instar, 4th instar.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Integrated Pest Management (IPM) (1)]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[This is a multi-faceted approach for managing pests by combining biological, cultural, physical, and chemical tools in a way that minimizes economic, health, and environmental risks.  IPM stresses low toxicity and the use of non-pesticides when possible.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Integrated Pest Management (IPM) (2)]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A comprehensive plan for preventing or controlling a pest problem, based on the total situation; the why of the pest problem. (IPM may include a combination of possible controls: facilities management, mechanical, physical, biological, regulatory, and chemical controls, as appropriate to the situation.)]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Intertidal areas below the mean high water mark]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[An area between the extremes of high and low tides which is rather low and may retain water or may dry out. If a pesticide is applied here the water will be contaminated during high tides]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Intracellular Parasites]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pathogens such as those of the genus-species, rickettsia spp; like viruses, they cannot live outside a living cell]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Invader Species]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[One of several stored product pests, such as the flour beetle, that enters packages through openings]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Inverse relationship]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[In mathematics, an inverse relationship means that as one variable (like velocity) gets larger, another variable (like amount of pesticide applied) gets proportionally smaller, such that the product of the two variables remains the same.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Invertebrates]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Animals with no backbone. In the kingdom Animalia animals belonging to these phyla are invertebrates:  Annelida (e.g., segmented worms), Mollusca (e.g., clams), Arthropoda (e.g., insects).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[IPM]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Integrated Pest Management.  A strategy of reducing pests by using a variety of suitable techniques that may include chemical and non-chemical methods.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[IPMIS]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Integrated Pest Management Information System.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[J]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Jacobson's Organ]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Sensory apparatus on the roof of a snake's mouth.  The snake collects chemicals from the environment and brings them to the Jacobson's organ. Using its forked tongue a snake can sense many things from the environment, such as the presence of prey species, or the location of a potential mate during mating season.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Juvenile hormones]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Synthetic growth hormones that disrupt insect life cycles by preventing maturation.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[K]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Khapra Beetle]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A beetle accidentally introduced to several places in the United States that is an extremely destructive grain pest. "Khapra" means destroyer in Sanskrit.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[King]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The king and queen are primary reproductives that have managed to mate and begin a colony. (Alates who make it good.)]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Kingdom]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[This is the highest order of biological classification based on life forms that share fundamental similarities.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[L]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Liquid, a pesticide formulation that is already in a liquid form]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Lambda-Cyhalothrin]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The active ingredient (a.i) in DEMAND Pest Tab; a pyrethroid nerve poison.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Larder Beetle]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Named for the larder, the pantry or cellar where food is stored; often found in houses--and not just in the larder (the kitchen); they eat food in the kitchen or pantry.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Larva]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The immature stage (between egg and pupa) of an insect having complete metamorphosis. A butterfly is an insect with complete metamorphosis.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Lateral]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pertaining to the side, either the left or right side.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Lateral Movement]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Movement of herbicide across sloping ground after rain into non-target areas.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[LC50]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Known as a toxicity value. The lethal concentration of chemical in the air inhaled by land animals or absorbed through the gills of fish in water, which causes death in half of the exposed test population. (Test subjects are typically mice or rats for air concentrations; fish for water concentrations). Chemical is administered as a single exposure (typically 1 or 4 hours). This value gives you an idea of the relative toxicity of the material. This value applies to vapors, dusts, mists, gases, fumigants, and materials dissolved in water.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[LD50]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Known as a toxicity value. The lethal dosage, amount of solid or liquid which causes death in half of the exposed population when administered orally or dermally.  (The toxicity value is measured in milligrams of toxin per kilograms of body weight. Thus pounds have to be converted to kilograms.) The lower the LD<font size]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Leaching]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(1) Downward movement or percolation of herbicide through a porous medium such as soil. (2) The process by which soluble matter is dissolved in groundwater and carried downward and radially through the soil, sometimes into groundwater. Example: rainwater carrying an herbicide down the slope and into another field.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Leading edge]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The part of the termite wing closest to the head. This is the part that cuts through the air first, as the termite flies forward.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Leptospirosis]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[An infectious disease in domestic animals, especially cattle, swine, and dogs (also raccoons), caused by spirochetes of the genus Leptospira and characterized by fever and jaundice (2) Disease transmitted through contact with rat urine.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Lesser Grain Borer]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Mainly attacks wheat, corn, rice and millet. Both the larvae and adults are primary pests. They bore irregularly shaped holes into whole, undamaged kernels and the larvae, immature stages, may develop inside the grain. Larval and adult feeding in and on grain kernels may leave only dust and thin brown shells. A sweet, musty odor is often associated with infestations of this insect.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Lethal dose formula ]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Lignin]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A complex polymer, the chief non-carbohydrate constituent of wood. Lignin binds to cellulose fibers and hardens and strengthens the cell walls of plants.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Line of sight supervision]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Supervision in which the supervisor can physically see the pesticide application and observe his work at all times.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Lipid synthesis inhibitors]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Herbicides that work by preventing the production of fatty acids vital to the integrity of cell membranes, and thus, growth. Examples include fenoxyprop and sethoxydim.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Live Trapping]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A means of detecting ectoparasites that may be harbored by rodents whereby the rodent is knocked out with chloroform, placed in a white porcelain tray, and its fur is combed through. Any ectoparasites dislodged by combing can be seen against the white background, collected for identification, and tested for disease.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Loreal Pit]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Sensory organ of pit vipers, such as the rattlesnake, copperhead, and water moccasin.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Lot]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[One cycle of production from a mill or food processing plant; could be one or many lots per day.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Low-Volatility Pesticide]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A pesticide that doesn't evaporate under normal conditions of temperature and pressure.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Lyme Disease]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Disease vectored by deer mice, transmitted by the bite of a tick.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Lymphocytic Choriomeningitis]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A form of viral meningitis caused by a virus carried by the common house mouse.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[M]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[MACOM]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Acronym for major command.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Maggot]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The larval, worm-like stage of a fly's life cycle.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[MAJCOM]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Air Force Term for Major Command.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Malpighian tubules]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[One of a group of long, slender excretory tubules at the anterior end of the hindgut in insects and other terrestrial arthropods.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Mandible]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[This is one of the first pair of arthropod mouthpart appendages, typically a jaw-like chewing organ.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Marine borer]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A generic term for any marine organism that destroys wood. The most destructive of these organisms is the shipworm, or teredo, and the gribble. Gribbles are crustaceans and shipworms are mollusks (like clams or oysters), but both of them like to colonize wood. Shipworms (teredos) bore cylindrical holes in wood, including wooden ships! Gribbles generally colonize marine pilings. Both of these animals can degrade wood to the point that it's completely destroyed.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Mass Per Unit Volume]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Commonly an MSDS will report toxicity in terms of milligrams of toxin per liter of volume (parts per million) or milligrams of toxin per cubic meter (1,000 liters).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Material Safety Data Sheet (MSDS)]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[LD50 and LC50 values are found on the MSDS, not the label. The MSDS is written or printed material concerning a hazardous chemical that includes information on the chemical's identity, physical and chemical characteristics, physical and health hazards, primary routes of entry, exposure limits, whether the chemical is a carcinogen, precautions for safe handling and use, control measures, emergency and first aid procedures, the date of preparation of the MSDS or the last change to it, and the name, address, and telephone number of the manufacturer, importer, or employer distributing the MSDS.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Mating flight]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The behavior in which primary reproductives leave the colony and fly out in an attempt to mate and ultimately establish a new colony. ]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Mechanical control (of weeds)]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Reduction of pest plant population by hand or through the use of mechanical devices.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Mechanical Vector]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A vector that simply carries a microorganism with no replication occurring. A house fly, for example, can pick up Salmonella spp. on its feet from feces and then deposit it on human food.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Medial]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pertaining to the middle of a segment or an appendage.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Medial line]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A line that runs from the anterior to the posterior and divides the animal in half.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Mediterranean Flour Moth]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Found on a great variety of foodstuffs in addition to flour, grain residues (insect-infected grain, broken kernels, and dust), and various whole grains. Not as serious a pest as the Indian meal moth and some of the grain infesting beetles, but it still causes clogging of machinery with its webbing, and at times causes grain mill shut-downs. In recent times, the use of fumigants has greatly reduced the incidence of the Mediterranean flour moth.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Meniscus]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A curve in the surface of a liquid produced in response to the surface of the container or another object. For water, the curve will be concave. When reading a scale on the side of a container filled with liquid, the meniscus must be taken into account in order to obtain an accurate measurement.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Metabolic poisons]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pesticides that kill by altering some physiological process vital to pest survival, such as nervous system function or energy metabolism]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Metamorphosis]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(1) A change in form during development.  The change from nymph or immature stage to adult stage. Metamorphosizing arthropods can be mistaken for an entirely different class of animals. (Example:  When flea larvae (with a worm-like in appearance) are found in a pet's bed, they  can be mistaken for worms. In fact, they are actually baby fleas.  Another common error is to mistake grub worms, immature beetles in the larval stage, for the beneficial annelid worm. Beetles are arthropods from the Class Insecta and they feed on grass. Annelid worms are another phylum entirely. Look for the physical  characteristics. A grub is an insect with a head, thorax and 3 legs. An annelid worm lacks these physical characteristics. (2) A change, or changes, in form during the growth of an animal, which adapt it to a new environment or way of living.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Metamorphosis, complete]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Of the arthropods, only animals belonging to the class Insecta go through complete metamorphosis, which involves  four stages:  egg, larva, pupa, and adult.  In complete metamorphosis there is a dramatic change between larval and adult insects. Looking at a worm-like white grub in the compost pile, you would never imagine the iridescent June beetle that it will become. Complete metamorphosis gives arthropods a distinct advantage by allowing adults and young to use different food sources.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Metamorphosis, Incomplete]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Incomplete or gradual metamorphosis occurs in such insects as:  crickets, grasshoppers, and cockroaches. The immature insect generally looks like the adult, eats the same food, and frequents the same habitat, but it is not sexually mature and lacks wings.  The life cycle for gradual metamorphosis has 3 stages, with the insect going from an egg to a nymph or immature to an adult.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Metamorphosis, simple]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Of the arthropods, animals belonging to the classes, Crustacea, Arachnida, Diplopoda, and Chilopoda go through simple metamorphosis. The immature insect resembles the adult, except it's usually smaller. The arthropod molts repeatedly and grows, but the overall body form does not change over time. This means that nymphs and adults are exactly alike, except that adults are sexually mature, while nymphs are immature. Lower arthropods, such as silverfish and cockroaches always eat the same food in every life stage. Thus immature nymphs get pushed aside by hungry adults.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Methane]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A gas given off by animal waste. It can be used as fuel, but the process to turn it into fuel is very expensive, so this is not done very often. Methane is a greenhouse gas, which means that it contributes to global warming.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Metochlor]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Widely used in agriculture as a pre-emergent control for grassy weeds.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Metering knob]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The metering knob adjusts the flow of pesticide when the machine is in a liquid configuration.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Metering nozzles]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[When the pressure pump is installed, the metering knob is removed and flow is governed by a metering nozzle. Pesticide passes through the nozzle into the air flow. Metering nozzles come in three sizes, small to large. Using a larger nozzle creates a faster flow.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Me-Too Pesticides]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Copy-cat pesticides manufactured under a different name. Product testing has been done for the original pesticide (Methyl Ethyl Doom manufactured by company A), thus making registration for the "Me-too" pesticide ("Jim's Methyl Ethyl Death" manufactured by company B) faster and easier.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Microbials]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A class of pesticides whose active ingredient is a microbe or a microbial protein.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Microfilariae]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Tiny thread-like larvae of filarial worms. People infected with river blindness harbor larvae in their blood, which develop into adult filarial worms which, in turn, mate and produce thousands of offspring called microfilariae.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Midges]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Any of numerous minute dipterous insect (houseflies, mosquitoes, gnats), somewhat resembling a mosquito.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Miscible]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Mixable.  Once mixed, the substances will not separate or settle out.  Sport drink powders are miscible; oil and vineger (as in salad dressing) are not.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Misting]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Residual liquid pesticide application in which droplet sizes are 50-100 microns.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Mites]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Tiny arachnids (small animals with 8 legs) which often live as parasites on animals, or plants or in prepared foods.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Miticides]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pesticides that kill mites.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[MMF]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Monomolecular film. As in Agnique MMF.  This one-molecule thick molecular film covers water surfaces and prevents some aquatic insects, such as mosquito larvae and pupae, from breathing.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Mode of Action]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The mechanism (physical, mechanical, or biochemical) by which the pesticide affects the pest. The least toxic pesticides work physically or mechanically on the pest, as with desiccants and insecticidal soaps.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Molluscicides]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pesticides that kill mollusks (slugs, snails, oysters, squids etc).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Mollusks]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Animals with a soft body of then enclosed in a shell, such as oysters, snails, squids, etc.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Molt]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Periodic shedding of the cuticle in arthropods or the outer skin in reptiles.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Molting]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(1) The process of shedding the exoskeleton (2) Process by which immature arthropods and other animals shed skin, etc., that will be succeeded by new growth. (During simple metamorphosis, the arthropod molts repeatedly and grows, but the overall body form does not change over time. This means that nymphs and adults are exactly alike, except that adults are sexually mature, while nymphs are immature.)]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Monitoring]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Surveying the pesticide problem repeatedly over time in order to confirm or revise the proposed IPM strategy.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Monomolecular Film]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Monomolecular Film. As in Agnique MMF. This one-molecule thick molecular film covers water surfaces and prevents some aquatic insects, such as mosquito larvae and pupae, from breathing.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Morphology]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Branch of biology dealing with the form and structure of plants and animals.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Mound Drenching]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Method of ant control in which a few gallons of insecticide diluted with water are poured into an ant mound.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[MSDS]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Material Safety Data Sheet.  A written document that provides product users and emergency personnel with information and procedures needed for handling and working with chemicals.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Mucocutaneous]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Affecting the mucous membrane and skin surface; as in mucotaneous leishmaniasis, which eats away at the nose and mouth.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Mucocutaneous Leishmaniasis]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A form of leishmaniasis that eats away at the mucous membranes and skin of the nose and mouth.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Multiple Dose Rodenticides]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Rodenticides that kill rodents or cause serious human illness only with multiple exposures, rather than a single exposure. (Example: Warfarin, which belongs to the multi-dose Coumarins.)]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Murine]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pertaining to rats and mice.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Murine Typhus]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Disease transmitted by the bite  of the Oriental rat flea.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Mutualistic]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A relationship between two organisms of different species that benefits both and harms neither.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Mutualists]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Two or more species that derive benefit from interaction, often in the form of food or defense.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Mycelium]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The hypha or mass of hyphae that make up the body of a fungus.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Myiasis]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The invasion of living tissue of animals by larvae of Diptera (flies).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[N]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[National Stock Number (NSN)]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Not found on the label, but available from the Standard Pesticide List maintained on the Armed Forces Pest Management Board website. The national stock number or NSN usually doesn't change.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Natural Organic Insecticides]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Carbon-containing pesticides taken directly from the natural world, such as botanical insecticides and petroleum products.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[NAVFAC]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Naval Facilities Command]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Navy Environmental Health Centers (NEHC)]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The Naval Environmental Health Command (NEHC) mission is to ensure Navy and Marine Corps readiness through leadership in prevention of disease and promotion of health. We are the Navy's authoritative source for FHP support, providing a full spectrum of preventive health services.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Necrosis]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A type of cell death in which cells swell and break open, release their contents and can damage neighboring cells and provoke inflammation.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Necrotizing Venom]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Venom that attacks living tissues around the site of a wound, rather than attacking whole body systems. Generally there is no sensation of pain, initially.  The brown recluse spider injects necrotizing venom with its bite.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Nematicides]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pesticides designed to kill or otherwise control nematodes.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Nematodes]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(1) Worms in long, cylindrical unsegmented bodies, such as hookworms, pinworm, etc. (2) Non-segmented roundworms belonging to the phylum Nematoda--one of the most successful of all animal groups. Most nematodes live in soil, feeding on decaying organic matter, other microbes, or plant roots. Nematodes that parasitize people are called filarial worms.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Nematology]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The study of nematodes, or roundworms. Many nematodes cause disease in living things and problems in agriculture.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[NEPA]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The National Environmental Policy Act (NEPA) requires that the environmental impact of all major federal actions be considered before implementing an installation pest management plan.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Nettles]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Plants covered with stinging hairs as a form of defense against being eaten.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Nettling]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Stinging or irritating--as in nettling spines of urticating caterpillars.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Neurotoxic Venom]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Venom that attacks the nervous system, causing reactions such as muscle spasms, pain, irregular heartbeat. Poisonous snakes, most scorpions, and widow spiders inject neurotoxic venom with their bite.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Neurotoxin]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A substance that inhibits, damages, or destroys the tissues of the nervous system.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Nitrogen-fixing]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The conversion of atmospheric nitrogen into compounds that plants and other organisms can assimilate, usually accomplished by microorganisms.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Nits]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The eggs of a louse.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Non-Appropriated Fund Activities]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[For-profit operations that fund themselves (and get no appropriations from Congress), such as: the golf course, bowling alley, commissary, and PX. (Golf courses are the largest single users of pesticides in the DOD.)]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Non-Repellant Pesticides]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Inorganic insecticides are non-repellant, especially to cockroaches]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Nonselective Contact Herbicide]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Herbicide chemicals that are capable of killing most plants, grasses or broadleaf. There are 4 types: soil fumigants, soil sterilants, systemic non-persistent foliage applied chemicals, and non-persistent foliage applied chemicals.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Non-social Predators]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The vast majority of  scorpions are nonsocial, solitary animals that interact only at birth, during courtship, or for cannibalism.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Non-traceable pesticides]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pesticide purchased and used by individuals in Family Housing or sometimes in the offices around the installation, and not reported.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Nozzle calibration]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[a technique for converting gallons per acre, which are difficult to measure, into an easily measured unit, gallons per minute.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Nymphs]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The immature stage of an insect that does not have a pupal stage, such as a cockroach. Nymphs look similar to adults.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[O]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Obligate Parasites]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Parasites that can only survive as parasites, that is, by feeding on a live host; they have no alternate means of surviving. Example: ticks must parasitise living animals, such as human beings, because blood is their only source of food.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Obligately Intracellular Parasite]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A parasite that can only develop inside a living cell, such as Rickettsia rickettsii, the pathogen that causes Rocky Mountain Spotted Fever.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Off-target application]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[when non-target shrub or pest is killed, e.g.,  shrubbery  dies after the lawn has been treated for weeds.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Omnivores]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[An animal that eats both plants and other animals; domestic rodents are omnivores.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Ootheca]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A type of egg mass made by any member of a variety of species (usually insects or mollusks) and containing many eggs surrounded by a foam of protein which may then harden into a tough casing for protection. Notable ootheca-making insects are the mantid (praying mantis) and cockroach.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Opportunistic Pathogen]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pathogen that will spread to almost any living organism, such as, Fransisella tulernsis, the bacterium which causes Tularemia.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[O-ring]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A round rubber washer or gasket that is compressed to create a watertight or liquid-proof seal, typically in a compression fitting. O-rings are made of rubber or plastic, and they can dry out and crack. Some grease, or a drop of oil, keeps them pliable.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Oral (and dermal) toxins]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Toxins ingested through the mouth or absorbed through the skin. Measured using LD50 values.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Oral absorption]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Occurs when a toxin is eaten or drunk, as in the case of children eating rodent or insect bait.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Order]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A subdivision of a class, containing a group of related families.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Order Acarina]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Mites (and ticks) belong to this order.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Order Coleoptera]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Beetles belong to this order. Coleoptera means sheath wings, wings that protect the body of the insect.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Order Lepidoptera]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Moths belong to this order. Lepidoptera means scaly wings.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Organelles]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Literally, the term means "Little organs". Inside a cell, there are various structures that perform specific functions, much like the multicellular organs of our body carry out certain tasks.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Organic compounds (rodenticides)]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A class of rodenticides, either natural or synthetic, which contain carbon. Virtually all currently used rodenticides, both anti-coagulants and non-anticoagulants, are organic compounds.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Organic Insecticides]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Contain carbon]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Organometalic]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A chemical formed when a metal or metalloid binds to the carbon in an organic compound. Some oil-borne wood preservatives, such as copper chromated arsenate, are organometalics.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Organophosphates]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Along with organophosphates, carbamates are highly toxic and the most dangerous group of pesticides. Carbamates and organophosphates kill by cholinesterase inhibition, and attack the nervous system, causing loss of muscular control. (Injuries from carbamates are more easily reversible than those of organophosphates.)]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Overwintered]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Insects that survive the winter.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Oviposit]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[To lay eggs; a term usually used to define egg-laying by insects, who have a specialized structure called an ovipositor.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Ovipositor]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Specialized egg-laying organ which in most insects is formed from outgrowths of the eighth and ninth abdominal segment. Extreme forms of ovipositor occur in the sawflies, ichneumons, and wood wasps, where it may be longer than the entire body, and equipped apically with saw teeth to aid penetration of hard plant tissues.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[P]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Palps]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Male sexual structures used to identify the hobo spider under the microscope.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Parasitic fungi]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Fungi that live on, or in another living thing (called the "Host" organism), and which cause either disease or reduced vitality in the host.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pathogen]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A disease-causing organism.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Parthenogenesis]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Reproduction by development of an unfertilized gamete]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pathologists]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Investigates structural and functional changes in tissues and organs which are caused by pesticidal compounds.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Peak Egg Hatch Period]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Many insect pests lay eggs during limited periods each year. This results in large, and predictable hatches. This information may be used in planning and conducting effective pest control.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pedicel]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A constriction between the thorax and abdomen found in insects in the  order hymenoptera (ants, bees, wasps, saw flies). This constriction is actually part of the abdomen, not a separate anatomical part.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pediculicide]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A pesticide used to kill lice.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pediculosis]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Head lice, a disease treated with pediculicide. Head lice do not vector other diseases, they are a disease themselves.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pedipalps]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A pair of claws on the scorpion's cephalothorax or front end used for grabbing prey and holding it in place as the scorpion sinks its fangs in; also used by for mating by mature males.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pendamethelin]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[One of the oldest pre-emergent herbicides. Can be used, for example, on corn seedlings.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Penetrant]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[An adjuvant that enhances the ability of a liquid to enter into the pores of a substrate or penetrate a surface layer.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Penetrator Species]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[One of several  stored product pests, such as the saw-toothed beetle, that readily chew through packages into stored food.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Percolation]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Seepage of a liquid, like water, through a porous body or surface, e.g., water percolating into ground water; pesticides seeping into drinking water. Rain may cause percolation as when pesticides wash down through sandy soil into underground water supplies.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Perennial]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Plant that lives for an indefinite period of years.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Perimeter Baiting]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Baiting strategy for either single or multiple-dose rodenticides that requires knowledge of rodent pathways. Bait is set around the perimeter of the building to keep rodents out. The problem is that it is hard to do, as surveillance of rodents is required.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Persistent Chemical]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A chemical or group of chemicals that are stable under normal situations and do not readily break down in the environment by microorganisms, heat, enzymes, or ultraviolet light.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pest]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Any injurious or annoying organism (plant, animal, fungus, virus, or microscopic organism).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pest Controller]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(Pesticide Applicator) Person who applies chemicals to manage or control pests.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pest management consultant]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Usually a graduate entomologist or agronomist who manages and directs the pest management program of an entire command or agency, providing policy, guidance and oversight.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pest management program]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The prevention and control of disease vectors and pests that may adversely affect the DOD mission or military operations; the health and well-being of people, structures, materiel or property. (From DODI 4150.7, DoD Pest Management Program).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pest Quarantine]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Geographic isolations of pest organisms imposed to prevent the spread of disease and/or destruction,. e.g., browntree snakes.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pesticide]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The term applies to many kinds of ingredients in products, such as insect repellants, weed killers, disinfectants and swimming pool chemicals, which are designed to prevent, destroy, repel or reduce pests of any sort. Any substance, including biological control agents that may prevent, destroy, repel, or mitigate pests. If a product is sold as a pesticide, it must be registered at the federal level by the EPA and the state level by an agency such as the state's department of agriculture. EPA-registered pesticides must carry labels describing the proper dosage and frequency of application for the control of specific pests, as well as a list of active ingredients and other pertinent information.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pesticide applicator]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Any individual who applies pesticides or supervises the use of pesticides by others (From DODI 4150.7, DoD Pest Management Program).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pesticide categories]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Categories (I-IV, with Cat I being the most toxic). The categories indicate whether an antidote statement is required on the label and where (on the front or on the back). These categories are linked to levels of toxicity. (See Cat I, Cat II, Cat III, Cat IV.).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pesticide residue]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The pesticide component left over long after the pesticide application is completed.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pesticide resistance]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(1) Phenomenon by which target plant, herb, or rodent develops tolerance for the poison, such that it no longer is effective in eradicating it.  An organism's defenses against the action of a pesticide that render it partly or wholly ineffective. Some organisms are able to metabolize or otherwise deactivate specific pesticides. Tolerance developed by pests to pesticides such that the pesticide loses its ability to control pests. (2) Undesirable result of repeated application of one pesticide exclusively on the same active site, e.g., exclusive use of the organophosphate (Malathion) for mosquito control at a given site. The pest population becomes less susceptible to the effects of the pesticide. (To avoid pesticide resistance use targeted application, pesticide rotation, and no-chemical measures, where possible.).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pesticide runoff]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[What occurs when pesticides wash across the ground in rainwater or other moving water. Pesticides can make their way to lakes, rivers, and streams in two basic ways. They can hitch a ride with eroding soil by adsorbing, or attaching, to soil particles. Or, they can dissolve in runoff water and move with the water as it flows across the surface.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pesticide tank]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Receptacle for liquid and granular pesticides.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pesticide tolerances]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Amount of pesticide residue, which is considered safe in good products. Any amount exceeding the tolerance is considered harmful.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pesticide tube]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Conducts liquid pesticides from the spray tank to the misting nozzle.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Petroleum-Based Pesticides]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Like horticultural (or dormant) oils, they are made from lightweight petroleum. A lot of pesticides are mixed with petroleum.) Exposure causes nausea, coughing, vomiting, weakness, dizziness, slow and shallow breathing.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pheromone traps]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[the use of pheromones to trap insects, a form of bio-control; entomologists duplicate insect sex pheromones and use them in traps to catch the male insects.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pheromone]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A chemical substance that conveys information to and produces specific responses in certain animals.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pheromone trail]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A type of pheromone used by social insects and some lepidopterans to recruit others of its species to a food source.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Phloem]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Greek word for bark. Refers to the living vascular tissue located just beneath the outer bark of trees that moves manufactured sugars from foliage to other growing parts of the plant, especially the roots.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Photoperiodicity]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(1) The relative amount of daylight (or night) during a day. (2) Reaction in an invertebrate to the relative amount of daylight or darkness. (Hibernation is triggered by photoperiodicity.)]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Photosynthesis inhibitors]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Herbicides that inhibit the plant's food production system by binding to specific sites within the chloroplast. Plants rapidly starve and die. Examples include atrazine, prometon, diuron and bromocil.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Phylum]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[This is one of the dozen or so divisions in the animal kingdom. Class a subdivision of a phylum, containing a group of related orders.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Phylum Arthropoda]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Consists of the 5 classes of arthropods:   1. Diploda (millipedes),   2. Chilopoda (centipedes),   3. Insecta (insects),   4. Arachnida (spiders, ticks and scorpions), and   5. Crustacea (shrimp and lobsters).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Physical tools (IPM)]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Use of physical forces (heat, cold, radioactivity) to control pests usually in confined spaces.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Physogastry]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A condition in arthropods in which the females ovaries and fat bodies enlarge, causing abdominal enlargement.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Phytotoxic]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Poisonous to plants. A lot of common materials, such as oils, easily kill plants. Over application of pesticides may also have a phytotoxic effect, even if the pesticides are insecticides and not designed to harm plants at all.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pi]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The ratio of the circumference to the diameter of a circle; a number having a value to eight decimal places of 3.14159265 and usually rounded off to 3.14]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pigment inhibitors]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Herbicides that stop the synthesis of carotenoid, a photosynthetic pigment important in plant food production. Plants exposed to pigment inhibitors turn white and soon die. Examples include: clomazone, norfluazon, benzofenap, and amitrole.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Piscicides]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pesticides that kill fish]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Piston pump]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A pump in which motion and pressure are applied to the fluid by a reciprocating piston in a cylinder. Also known as reciprocating pump.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Plant growth regulators]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Herbicides with multiple modes of action. Their primary mode of action is not known. They have properties similar to auxin (a growth hormone produced by plants). They interfere with nucleic acid metabolism and normal transport systems in plants by induced massive cell proliferation. Examples include "2,4-D", dicamba, and clopyralid.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Plasmodium]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Parasitic protozoan, belonging to the genus Plasmodium; pathogen (agent) which causes malaria]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Poison (Toxicant)]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A substance that causes injury, or illness, or death; usually effective even in very small dosages. Remember that the dose makes the poison.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Polymer]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[""A plastic-like material produced from chemical ""Monomers"""" which in turn have been produced from alcohols and petrochemicals. Certain polymers are used as latex paint and caulk binders. The binder's polymer particles are small and carried in water. The lignin in wood is a polymer.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Positive Displacement]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A mechanism by which gas or fluid is displaced, or pushed, out of a chamber. Positive displacement pumps conduct fluid into a chamber, and then use a piston to push that liquid from the chamber and into a discharge pipe.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Post-Emergent Herbicide]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A chemical applied as an herbicide to the foliage of established weeds.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Posterior]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Hind part or in the rear.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Precipitate]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A solid substance that forms in a liquid and settles to the bottom of a container.  A material that no longer remains in suspension.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Predacides]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pesticides that kill vertebrates.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pre-Emergent Herbicides]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A chemical applied as an herbicide to the seedling root of the weed before it emerges from the ground as an established weed. Pre-emergent herbicides are virtually insoluble, or they'll wash down to the soil surface, but not below the surface. They barely react with water at all.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pressure]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The force exerted on a given area. In the U.S., pressure is often measured in units of pounds per square inch.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Primary reproductives]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The fertile, winged termite caste that takes mating flights in an effort to establish new colonies.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Primer bulb]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Used to "Prime" the engine just before starting by injecting a little gasoline into the carburetor.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Primitive termites]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Termites in 3 of the 4 termite families (Hodotermitidai, Kalotermitidae, and Rhinotermitidae) which are characterized by relatively simple caste division and development compared to termites in the family Termitidae. Subterranean, dampwood, and drywood termites are considered primitive termites.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Private certification]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A certification that authorizes farmers to use or supervise the use of restricted use pesticides on their own farm to produce an agricultural commodity.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Proboscis]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Also known as a beak; the elongated, protruding insect mouth parts, adapted for sucking or piercing. When taking a blood meal, female files use the prosboscis to cut into the victim's skin.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Producer]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The company that manufactures a pesticide. The registrant listed on the label may not necessarily be the producer/manufacturer.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Prolegs]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The fleshy leg-like structures on the caterpillar which occur on the abdomen behind the actual front legs.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Promenade-a-deux]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[French for walking in pairs; term used to describe scorpion mating in which male deposits a spermatophore on a rock or other surface, then guides the female into a position in which she can take up the spermatophore and be inseminated.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pronotum]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(1) The dorsal body plate of the first section of the thorax, frequently enlarged in many insects, such as cockroaches; it acts as a shield covering the head. (2) The upper or dorsal surface of the first segment of the thorax. This segment bears the anterior (first pair) of legs but no wings.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Propellant]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A gas, as a fluorocarbon, that serves as a vehicle for discharging the contents of an aerosol container. Propellants fall into the category of inert ingredients, so many aerosol insecticides do not list them specifically. Not all propellants are fluorocarbons, but they are all pressurized gasses of some type.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Prophylactic]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(See Prophylaxis)]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Prophylaxis]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Anything that prevents or contributes to the prevention of disease, such as certain drugs, fresh air, rest, and proper nutrition.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Proportion]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A relationship between two equal ratios, or fractions, used to solve for missing or unknown quantities. Note that all proportions are equations.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Proprietary Secrets]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Trade secrets, which are the legal property of the manufacturer]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Protocerebrum]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The primitive anterior cerebral vesicle; the first part of the arthropod brain.  The arthropod "brain" is actually a collection of ganglia compressed into a single organ made up of the:  protocerebrum, deuterocerebrum, and tritocerebrum.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Protozoan]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Single-celled parasite  that can cause disease, that is, serve as a pathogen (agent).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Proximal]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Near the body. The part of a segment or appendage that is closest to the body.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pseudergate]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA["Known" also as false workers; this is an intermediate termite stage that can molt into virtually any of the main castes; worker, soldier and reproductive.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[PSI]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pounds per square inch; unit used to measure pressure, such as the force of air inflating a tire, or the force exerted by moving fluids like water coming out of a hose, pressure washer, or pesticide sprayer.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Psittacosis]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Also known as parrot fever; a bacterial disease contracted by inhaling dried bird secretions that can lead to pneumonia.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pulsed Baiting]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Baiting strategy for single-dose rodenticides. Baits are set out in pulses or spaced intervals, for example, every 2 weeks. In this way, each pulse removes a different group of rodents.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pupa]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(1) An insect in the non-feeding, usually immobile, transformation stage between the larva and adult. (2) Intermediate stage between the larva and the adult; this stage is generally inactive and encased in a case or cocoon.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pupal stage]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The nonfeeding stage between the larva and adult in insects with complete metamorphosis, during which the larva typically undergoes complete transformation within a protective cocoon or hardened case.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pupate]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[To become a pupa, that is, an insect in the non-feeding , usually immobile, transformation state between the larval and adult stages.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pupation]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The process of changing into a pupa, the non-feeding, usually immobile, transformation state between the larval and adult insect stages.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[PVNTMED SVC]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Preventive Medicine Service]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pyrethroids]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Copies, or analogs, of the botanical pesticide, pyrethrum.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Pyrethrum and pyrethroids]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Exposure causes skin irritation, pre-asthmatic reactions, hay-fever-like symptoms, and convulsions.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Q]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Quarantine]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A strict isolation imposed to prevent the spread of a disease, or pest.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Queen]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The king and queen are primary reproductives that have managed to mate and begin a colony. (Alates who make it good.)]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Questing]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A tick behavior consisting of climbing onto vegetation, usually along animal trails, and extending their front two legs. When a passing animal brushes against the questing tick, the tick grabs and holds on, then looks for a feeding site.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Quinine]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A chemical compound which serves as a natural cure for malaria. Found in the bark of cinchona trees.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[R]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Radius]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A straight line from the center to the perimeter of a circle (or from the center to the surface of a sphere.)]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Rain Fast]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Phenomenon that occurs within a few hours of herbicide application, whereby the herbicide becomes impervious to the potential diluting effect of rain.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Rat Bite Fever]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Rat-borne disease transmitted by contact with rat saliva. Rats leave their saliva in the bowls or cups of your pantry, then you unknowingly drink out of them.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Red Flour Beetle]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[One of the Tribolium flour beetles; The red and confused flour beetles live in the same environment and compete for resources. The red flour beetle may fly, especially before a storm, but the confused flour beetle does not fly. Very common pest infesting flour mills, warehouses, and grocery stores;  they also feed on grain, beans, dried fruits, nuts, chocolate, and other foods in the house.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Registered]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Refers to a pesticide with official sanction from a governing agency such as the USDA (until 1972) or EPA (after 1972), or a state (after 1978).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Registrant]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The party that registers the pesticide label. The registrant may not be the actual manufacturer. In this case, the label must specify the limited role of the registrant e.g., packed for, distributed by, sold by (to show that the name listed is not that of the producer).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Registration Number]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Like a social security number for pesticides. Always preceded by the words, EPA Registration Number. This number is unique to a particular pesticide made by a certain manufacturer. The same pesticide made by different manufacturers will have different registration numbers. Used as a tracking number on pesticide inventories, reports of pesticide usage, and incident reports.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Regulating flow rate]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Increasing or decreasing flow rate.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Relapsing Fever]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(1) An infection caused by bacteria in the Borrelia family. There are two major forms. Tick-borne relapsing fever (TBRF) is transmitted by the Ornithodoros tick and occurs in Africa, Spain, Saudi Arabia, Asia, and certain areas in the western US and Canada. Louse-borne relapsing fever (LBRF), which is transmitted by body lice, is prevalent in the developing world (Asia, Africa, and Central and South America). (2) A rickettsial disease vectored by lice and ticks, causing a periodic (every 3 - 5 days) fever.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Repellants]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Any substance such as lime, oil, etc. used to drive away pests or other insects.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Repugnatorial Fluid]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Toxic, carcinogenic substance, specifically, benzoquinones,  nasty yellowish substances that give a bad taste and odor to stored food; emitted from the glands of flour beetles (and other arthropods, such as millipedes).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Repugnatorial Glands]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Located at the base of the legs of millipedes, the gland squirts repugnatorial fluid at a distance of about one foot. This fluid is dangerous to the eyes and skin.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Reservoir]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Diseased animal in which the pathogen multiplies and can then be passed on. For plague, the reservoir is usually wild rodent populations. For Rocky Mountain Fever, ticks maintain the disease within themselves and also transmit or vector it. Just as a water reservoir stores water, a group of organisms can store pathogens. These organisms can then pass on the pathogen, either directly or through another vector. Reservoir animals may or may not be immune to the pathogen.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Residual Liquid Treatment]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The application of  residual liquid pesticide (normally a spray or mist) to some kind of surface where the pesticide stays.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Residual Solid Treatment]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The application of  residual solid pesticide (usually a dust or granule) to some kind of surface where the pesticide stays.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Residual Treatment]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A type of pesticide application intended to last and provide control over a period of time. Invariably, these treatments are applied to surfaces, such as floors, walls, and soil, or into a substance such as wood. This contrasts with airspace treatments, which are applied into the air and last no more than a few hours.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Residue]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The pesticide that remains in the environment in food, structures (buildings), soil, water, etc. after an application]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Resins]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Any one of a class of yellowish brown solid inflammable substances, of vegetable origin. Resins exude from trees in combination with essential oils, gums, etc., and in a liquid or semiliquid state. ]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Resistance]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A genetic change in response to selection by a pesticide, resulting in the development of strains capable of surviving a dose lethal to most individuals in a normal population. Resistance may develop in insects, weeds, or pathogens]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Restricted Use Pesticide]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A pesticide that can be purchased only by certified pesticide applicator and used only by certified pesticide applicators or persons directly under their supervision. Not available for use for the general public because of the high toxicities and/or environmental hazards. A pesticide that the EPA or State Regulatory agency determines to have the potential to cause unreasonable adverse effects on the environment or human health, when applied in accordance with the labeled direction for use, and has additional regulatory restrictions associated with it.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Resurveillance]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[a more detailed survey that occurs after the initial assessment, once you have confirmed that there truly is a pest management problem requiring an IPM strategy. During the resurvey, you return to the area to look at things in greater deta il to locate the habita t, determine population size and identify the a ttract ant.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Retention rate]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Amount of preservative (measured in pounds per cubic foot) that remains in wood after treatment is complete. This is a function of the type of treatment, the type of preservative, and the wood. Wood that's exposed to soil or water needs more preservative, so higher retention rates are used for wood that's in ground contact, or foundations.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Rhizomorphs]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A thick mass of hyphae forming a root-like structure characteristic of many fungi.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Rice Weevils]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Both granary and rice weevils, often known as "Snout weevils", penetrate and feed on the internal portions of whole grains during the larval (immature) stage, making early detection of infestations difficult. Usually found in grain storage or processing plants, infesting wheat, oats, rye, barley, rice, and corn. Although not often found in the home, sometimes they infest table beans, acorns, chestnuts, birdseed, sunflower seeds, and ornamental corn. Rarely found in macaroni and spaghetti.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Rickettsial Disease]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Diseases caused by pathogens from the genus-species, rickettsias spp; these pathogens are considered intracellular parasites--like viruses, they cannot live outside a living cell; almost all tick-borne disease are rickettsial.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Rinsate]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The contaminated water resulting from triple-rinsing empty pesticide containers.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Ripple effect]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Phenomenon in which any single act of  biotic simplification (removing any part of an ecosystem) leads to unexpected systemic consequences (one change leading to a series of changes) for the entire ecosystem. For example: pollinated crops failing after widespread mosquito control.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Risk]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The probability that an adverse effect will result from an exposure to a chemical.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Risk Formula]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[In toxicology, risk is considered to be the product of risk times exposure. Because exposure is controllable, so is risk.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Rodenticides]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pesticides designed to kill rodents are highly toxic to humans and come in 3 forms: organics, inorganics (such as zinc phosphide), or the newer anti-coagulant rodenticides. Anticoagulants inhibit blood-clotting leading to internal hemorrhage; inorganics destroy entire organ systems; organics are convulsants that induce heart attack.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Roosting]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A special word for avian slumber; birds often roost on a twig or branch in a sheltered area where they sit up straight and allow themselves to fall asleep. For safety and early warning purposes, birds are often found roosting in groups.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Running rough]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[An engine with an unstable combustion process. This instability may result from several different factors, but most likely the air/fuel mixture is incorrect. For example, leaving the choke closed after an engine has started will restrict air flow into the engine so that the fuel to air mixture is too rich. Without sufficient air for proper combustion, the engine will stutter and fuel will flood the spark plugs. Opening the choke will restore the proper fuel/air mixture and the engine will run smoothly.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[S]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[S.]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Solution. As in Orthene S]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Sample Eaters]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Rats and mice tend to take a bite of one food and then they move on to something else. This is probably a survival mechanism that helps them, to some extent, to keep them from eating anything toxic.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Sample Feeders]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(1) Animals that eat by tasting several of the foods available to them. By sampling and discarding foods, they spoil much more food than they actually eat. (2) Rats and mice tend to take a bite of one food and then they move on to something else. This is probably a survival mechanism that helps them, to some extent, to keep them from eating anything toxic.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Saprophytes]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Fungi and other organisms that receive nourishment from dead organic material.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Saturation Baiting]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Baiting strategy for multiple-dose rodenticides in which food is made constantly available. Spoiled or consumed baits are replaced daily. Baiting stations are spaced as follows: 15-50 ft. apart for rats, 10 ft. apart for mice]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Savanna (Savannah)]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A tropical or subtropical grassland containing scattered trees and drought-resistant undergrowth. Habitat of most tsetse flies.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Scientific Name]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Consists of the genus and species. (e.g., the scientific name for the Monarch butterfly is Danaus plexippus; the scientific name for humans is homo sapiens.)]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Scorpionism]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Poisoning by scorpions]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Seasoning]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A process of reducing the moisture content of wood, usually this is done by air-drying or kiln drying.  Wood treated with water-borne preservatives must be seasoned before using so that shrinkage can occur.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Secondary Pest]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(See Emergent Pest)]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Secondary poisoning]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Unintended poisoning of non-target animals that occurs when non-target animal consumes a pest which has been killed or sickened by a pesticide, e.g.,  birds that die after farms spray for grasshoppers]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Secondary Repellants]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Chemicals applied to crops or feed that don't immediately repel animals. Animals eating the treated food get sick and then associate their illness with the food]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Seedling growth inhibitors]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Herbicides normally used to control plants during germination. The site of action may be the root or the shoot, but the result is a reduction of new growth. Most of these herbicides inhibit cell division, or mitosis]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Seedling Root]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The Radicle, or embryonic root, is the first structure to emerge from a germinating seed. Pre-emergent herbicides must be applied to the seedling root.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Segmentation]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Division into parts. In humans, the spinal column is highly segmented into vertebrae. Arthropods are visibly divided into body parts or segments. Millipedes are highly segmented with 47-197 legs]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Selective Herbicides]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Herbicides that are toxic to some plants, but have little or no effect on other species.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Self-help]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pest management carried out by installation personnel do-it-yourselfers e.g., family housing occupants, using pest control materials (mainly glue traps, fly swatters, and very low toxicity pesticides, such as ant baits). Self-help usage must be accounted for in the installation pest management plan.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Serotypes]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The strain of a disease.  There are four serotypes or strains of the genus Flavivirus, the agent or pathogen that causes Dengue fever. There is no cross-immunity from one strain of the disease to the other. If you catch one serotype, you are not immune from catching the others.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Setae]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Specialized nettling spines; defense mechanism of caterpillar larva. Spines are hollow and filled with toxins from poison-gland cells. When these little needles break off, they release the toxin. Setae may penetrate human hide, or the toxins might just spill out on skin.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Shipworms]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Also known as teredos; a very destructive mollusk (in the same phylum as clams and oysters) that colonizes and destroys wood in marine environments. Shipworms generally drill cylindrical holes in wood, including wooden ships.  Shipworms (teredos) and the unrelated gribble are referred to as "marine borers" for their wood-destroying habits.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Silage]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Chopped green material, usually green corn, fermented in silos, then fed to animals in the winter.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Single Dose Rodenticides]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Highly toxic rodenticides that kill rodents or cause serious human illness with just a single exposure, rather after multiple exposures. (Example: diphacinone, one of the inandiones.)]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Site of application]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[This can be a crop or even an animal. Pesticide may be applied to any pest whose site of application is listed, even if the pest, itself, is not specifically mentioned on the label.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Social Insects]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(1) Insects that take bait back to colony before dying. (2) Insects, such as ants, termites bees, and most wasps, that live in colonies. They divide the labor in the nest so that different castes have different functions like reproduction, food-gathering and nest maintenance, and colony defense. These societies are almost completely female. Males only exist to fertilize the egg-laying queen. They usually die soon afterward.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Soil Fumigant]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[An herbicide that forms a gas toxic to plants, animals, and microorganisms.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Soil Solarization]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Sterilizing soil by covering it with clear plastic and letting sunshine heat it up to lethal temperatures. This technique may help replace the soil fumigant methyl bromide, which is being phased out because of its ozone depleting effects.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Soil Sterilant]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A chemical or agent that prevents the growth of all organisms present in the soil.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Soldier]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A termite caste modified for colony defense. Modifications include large mandibles used for fighting and a large head. Soldiers are unable to feed themselves.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Solubility]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[For pesticides, the active ingredient's ability to stick to vegetation or insect bodies.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Soluble]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A substance that will dissolve in a liquid carrier.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Solution]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A mixture of two or more substances that are completely dissolved.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Solvent]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A material having the property to dissolve another to form a solution.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Space Treatment]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A type of pesticide application in which the pesticide is applied to an airspace where the pest lives or will pass. Pests entering this airspace will inhale or contact the pesticide. Space treatments last a very short time and provide no lasting control.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Specialized Phase]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[In pesticide applicator training, this refers to training in any one of the ten commercial certification categories. In DoD, the specialized phase may cover category 2 (forestry), 3 (ornamental and turf), 5 (aquatic), 6 (right of way), 7 (industrial, institutional, structural and health related), 8 (public health) and 9 (aerial).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Species]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A group of individuals or populations similar in structure and physiology and capable of interbreeding and producing fertile offspring. They are different in structure and physiology from other groups and do not normally interbreed with them.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Sphincter]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A circular band of voluntary or involuntary muscle that surrounds orifices or openings in hollow organs, such as the stomach and intestine.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Spinosad]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Nervous system disruptor, derived from yeast. Used to control destructive caterpillars in turf grass and ornamental plants.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Spiracle]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[An opening through which air or water passes in the act of respiration]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Spiracles]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[All arachnids are terrestrial or land living arthropods.  They breathe by either spiracles or book lungs. The spiracles are breathing holes on the body surface that take air to individual cells.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Spittle]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Sticky foam produced when excess water is secreted]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Spores]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The reproductive unit of fungi. Spores function in the same way that seeds do for higher plants.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[SPP]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Abbreviation for the word "Species"; used to indicate that the insect has been identified only to the Genus level. (As in: Culex spp)]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Spray]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Residual liquid pesticide application in which droplet sizes are 100 microns or greater.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Spreader]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[An adjuvant used to enhance the spread of a pesticide over a treated surface, thus improving the coverage.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Squared]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Multiplying a number by itself, or raising the number to the second power. Area is measured in units squared.
]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Starter grip]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Link between the operator's hand and the starter rope.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Steroids]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A drug that enhances muscle growth if taken along with rigorous physical training and a high protein diet.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Sticker]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[An adjuvant used to improve the adherence of spray droplets to a plant, animal, or other treated surface.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Stomach poison]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A pesticide that must be eaten in order to have any toxic effect.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Stop cock]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Regulates pesticide flow.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Structural wood]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Lumber; furniture, flooring, wood paneling (some beetles, like lyctids, seem to prefer structural wood; others, like the cerambycids, typically feed on live trees and end up killing them in the process).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Structural wood]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Wood used to construct a building of some kind]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Stylet]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A small, stiff, needlelike organ or appendage]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Subcutaneous]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Lying under the skin, as tissue; living below the several layers of the skin, as certain parasites]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Sublimation]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Process by which a solid is converted to a gas without apparent liquefaction, e.g., dry ice (solid carbon dioxide) becomes a gas without passing through a liquid phase. In pest management, solid fumigants like aluminum phosphide become a gas without becoming a liquid.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Sump]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pit, well, or the like, in which water or other liquid is collected.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Superfund site]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Uncontrolled or abandoned place with hazardous waste that can possibly affect local ecosystems or people.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Supervise]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[In reference to restricted-use pesticide application, this means the certified person is "available" if needed. In DoD, this means the non-certified applicator is in line of sight of the certified supervisor. Under the law of most States, "available" means within the metropolitan area.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Surface gills]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[An organ for respiration under water. In some animals the gills can function in air if they do not become too dry.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Surface tension]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A property of liquids that forms cohesive forces near the surface.  The surface contracts and has properties similar to stretched elastic.  Small particles such as wettable powders will be unable to penetrate the surface. You may recall seeing insects such as water striders walking across a water surface because they don't break the surface tension.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Surface treatment]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A brush-on, or spray-on wood preservative treatment that covers the wood surface without penetrating into the wood.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Surface Waters]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Include lakes and ponds and rivers, as opposed to ground water, which is literally underground. Pesticides end up in surface water when they wash downhill from application sites or leaky storage buildings into water.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Surfactant]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[An inert ingredient that improves the spreading, dispersing, and/or wetting properties of a pesticide mixture.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Surveillance]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(1) Observing the pesticide problem as a first step towards developing an integrated pest management (IPM) strategy. (2) Thorough inspections or surveys made before or after pest management treatments to determine the presences and prevalence of pests or disease vectors (From DODI 41507, DoD Pest Management Program);  Observing the pesticide problem as a first step towards developing an integrated pest management (IPM) strategy.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Suspension]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Particles of a solid or unmixable liquid dispersed in a liquid or gas but not dissolved in it.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Symbiosis]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The intimate association of two kinds of organisms, like plants and fungi. If both organisms benefit from the association, it is called "Mutualism".]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Symbiotic]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A relationship of mutual benefit or dependence.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Synanthropy]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The urge to live in human settlements shown by domestic or filth flies, as well as other animals.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Synergist]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[substance used with pesticides to enhance their activity.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Synthetic organic insecticides]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Insecticides containing carbon, but developed in the laboratory instead of in the living world.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Systemic]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pertaining to or affecting the entire bodily system or the body as a whole.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Systemic Foliage Applied Herbicide]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Slow-acting herbicides that are applied to plant foliage and then absorbed and translocated within the plant, moving through the entire plant, killing the roots.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Systemic Herbicide]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Herbicide that is absorbed and translocated within a plant.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[T]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Targeted application]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[a pesticide application aimed directly at the problem pest or its habitat. Targeted application reduces the likelihood of pesticide resistance.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Taxonomic]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pertaining to the identification, naming and classification of organisms]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Telson]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Specially modified segment at the tip of the last segment (Tail) of a scorpion that contains the venom gland.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Tending]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Ant behavior that consists of protecting honeydew-producing insects from predators and sometimes moving them around to better feeding spots on the plant.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Termite Aggregation Pheromone]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Termites secrete an aggregation pheromone which is useful in marking paths to food and water sources.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Thermal Fogging]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A method of producing ultra-low volume aerosols in which pesticide is atomized into aerosol-sized droplets by means of heat.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Thigmotaxis]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Movement of an organism in response to contact with a solid body. Domestic rodents have positive thigmotaxis, meaning they LIKE to touch, especially solid forms like the edge of a wall.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Thoracic]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pertaining to the thorax. In insects and other arthropods the thorax is a body division consisting of several segments lying between the head and abdomen, to which are attached legs or other appendages.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Threshold planning quantity (TPQ)]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A baseline amount of an extremely hazardous substances. The baseline is established by federal guidelines. Any facility with extremely hazardous substance in amounts in excess of the threshold planning quantity is required to notify the state commission 60 days after the facility first begins handling an extremely hazardous substance in excess of its TPQ.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Throttle]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Controls flow of fuel into engine.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Toxic]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Poisonous to living organisms.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Toxicant]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A poisonous substance such as the active ingredient in a pesticide formulation.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Toxicity]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(1) A chemical's ability to alter a living tissue's metabolism.  This is a chemical property of a compound and cannot be modified except by destroying the compound. In this lesson, toxicity is classified according to the EPA system, into toxicity categories. The following terms are used: practically non-toxic, slightly toxic, moderately toxic, and highly toxic.  Keep in mind that toxicity can be quite variable within a specific class of insecticides. (2) The degree to which a substance is poisonous. Chemical property of compound; non-conditional (non-controllable characteristic cannot be amended). Toxicity cannot be changed, while exposure can be controlled. If you are not exposed to a highly fatal potent poison safely locked up in a cabinet there is zero risk.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Toxicity tables (inhalation)]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Lists the lethal concentration or LC50  of material that may be inhaled from the air. The amount of toxin is expressed as a fraction, milligrams of toxin per kilograms of body weight of a test animal.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Toxicity tables (oral and dermal)]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Lists the LD50  or lethal dose for solids and liquids that may be absorbed orally or dermally. The amount of toxin is expressed as a fraction, milligrams of toxin per liter of air or water (parts  per million).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Toxicologists]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Determine the levels at which pesticides become poisonous to humans and other organisms. Trace the metabolic pathway of pesticidal compounds in humans.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Toxicology]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The study of poisons and their effects.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Traceable pesticides]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Any pesticidal material used by a pest management professional on a government installation.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Trachea]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[In the respiratory system of arthropods, any of the small tubules branching throughout the body and conducting air from the exterior]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Tracheids]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The supporting and water-conducting cells (xylem) found in softwood trees.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Trachioles]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Air-conveying tubules forming the respiratory system of most insects, millipedes, centipedes, and many arachnids.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Trade names]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Another word for brand names. Trade names are great, and sometimes very colorful, but they change.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Transgenic Plants]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pesticide that inserts genes from other organisms into the plant.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Translocation]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The movement of food, water, or mineral solutes from one part of a plant to another.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Transovarial Passage]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Transmission of pathogen in an organism (such as a tick) from one generation to the next through the egg.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Transstadial Passage]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Transmission of pathogen from one stage of development to the next (e.g., nymphal to adult stage of the tick).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Tribolium Flour Beetles]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Beetles belonging to the genus Tribolium. Red flour beetles and confused beetles are Tribolium flour beetles.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Tritocerebrum]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The third or posterior division of the arthropod brain.  The arthropod "brain," is actually a collection of ganglia compressed into a single organ made up of the:  protocerebrum, deuterocerebrum, and tritocerebrum.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Trophallaxis]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The regurgitation of food by one animal for another. It is most highly developed in social insects such as ants and termites, in which individual colony members store food in their crops and regularly exchange it with other colony members and larvae to form a sort of communal stomach for the colony. It is also used by some vertebrates, such as birds feeding their young.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Trophic]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A group of organisms that occupy the same position in a food chain. For example, all green plants and other organisms capable of photosynthesis, as producers, occupy the first position on the food chain.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Two-cycle engine]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[An internal combustion engine that fires once for every revolution of the crankshaft. The two cycles are intake/compression and power/exhaust.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[U]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Ultra-Low Dosage Aerosol]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Indoor space treatment with liquid pesticide in which droplet sizes are between 5-30 microns.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Ultra-low volume]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Sprays that are applied at a rate of 0.5 gallons or less per acre or sprays and are applied in their undiluted form. (It may be useful to convert gallons of pesticide that will be sprayed from ultra-low volume equipment into ounces when doing inventory.)]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Ultra-Low Volume (ULV) Aerosol]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Outdoor space treatment with liquid pesticide in which droplet sizes are between 0.1 - 50  microns and application rates are very low--1/2 gallon of pesticide per acre-or LESS.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Unclassified Pesticides]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[General use pesticides that are not particularly hazardous to people or the environment when applied as directed. Anybody can buy and apply these, but they are still required to read the label and apply the pesticide in accordance with label instructions. However, for commercial application, the Department of Defense and many States require training and certification to apply these pesticides. Unclassified pesticides will not have any statement about this status.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Urticating Caterpillar]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Caterpillars that use urticating (or irritating/stinging) hairs as a defense.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Urtication]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Defensive behavior of caterpillars which involves stinging or whipping with nettles.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[UV-A]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Acronym for ultra-violet radiation A (Alpha) range; the longer wave spectrum of ultra-violet light used in black lights to detect rodent urine.  Ultraviolet radiation in the wavelength band of 0.32-0.40 m; a component of the spectrum of solar radiation that can tan human skin or cause redness in sensitive skin.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[V]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Vector]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[An insect or organism that carries a pathogen.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Vector Competence]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The ability to transmit a disease from one host to another. For example, body lice are Competent vectors of epidemic typhus, while head lice are unable to transmit the disease and are thus "Incompetent vectors".]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Venomous Insects]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Snakes, spiders and scorpions, and hymenopterans (wasps, bees, and ants).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Ventral]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Pertaining to the belly.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Vertebrates]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Animals with a backbone; animals belonging to the kingdom Animalia, phylum Vertebrata]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Vertical barrier]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Treating soil alongside basement walls or from the top of the slab to the bottom creates a vertical barrier.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Vesicating]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[(1) To cause or form blisters (2) Causing or forming blisters. The only threat from millipedes is  that when handled, they exude a defensive, vesicating liquid that causes the skin to blister. If left alone they will not cause harm.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Vessels]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The large diameter supporting and water conducting cells of hardwood trees.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Vibrissa]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Rodent whiskers]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Viperidae]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A family of reptiles in the suborder Serpentes found in Eurasia and Africa; all species are solehoglyphs--with moveable, rectractable front fangs. The fangs (or, more precisely, the maxillae) are laid back with the same action as when a pocket-knife is snapped together.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Visceral]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Affecting the viscera or internal organs; as in visceral leishmaniasis, which attacks the internal organs.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Visceral Leishmaniasis]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A form of leishmaniasis that attacks the internal organs.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Viscin]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A clear, tasteless substance extracted from the sap of the mistletoe]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[W]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Warning]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Human hazard signal word for moderately toxic pesticides.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Weather Blocks]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Solid rodenticide bait formulated with paraffin wax or some other stabilizing material so the food stays fresh for months. Can be tied to string and suspended just off the floor or nailed to the wall for rats to eat.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Weed and feed]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Fertilizer + pre-emergent herbicide mix.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Wet boom]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[a type of boom that carries liquid. Comprised of pipes with holes drilled at regular spaces. Nozzles are fitted into the holes.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Wettable powder]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A dry pesticide formulation in powder form which forms a suspension when added to water.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Wetting agent]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A wetting agent is a material similar to soap or detergent.  It decreases the toxicant.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Worker]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[A sterile termite caste that performs most of the colony maintenance, cares for other castes, and eats most of the wood.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Workload Definition Worksheet]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Document kept for each pest found on the installation that lists the type of damage caused and control strategies. (If there are 40 pests, there will be 40 separate workload definition worksheets.)]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[WP, W, or WWP]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Wettable powder. As in Decathlon WP]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[WSC, SC, or L]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Water soluble concentrate, a pesticide formulation that dissolves in water.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[WSP]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Water soluble packet (as in Merit 75 WSP).]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Xylem]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[The supporting and water-conducting tissues of vascular plants. (Xylem cells take different forms depending on the type of plant. For example, hardwood trees have large-diameter xylem cells called "vessels", whereas softwood trees have small-diameter xylem cells called "Tracheids".]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Z]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Zoonosis]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Disease that affects both humans and animals, such as: Leishmaniasis, African Sleeping Sickness, Tularemia, Oropouche, Anthrax.]]></definition>
    </term>
    <term>
      <name><![CDATA[Zoonotic Diseases]]></name>
      <definition><![CDATA[Diseases that under natural conditions are communicable from animals to humans, such as histoplasmosis, psittacosis and rabies.]]></definition>
    </term>
  </terms>
</glossary>
